{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS EXAMPLE) What President of Germany, who appointed Hitler Chancellor in 1933, was the\nnamesake of a zeppelin that caught fire above New Jersey in 1937?",
      "answer": [
        "Paul von Hindenburg",
        "Hindenburg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The William was scuttled by a storm before being subject to this event, which instead targeted\nthe Eleanor, Beaver, and Dartmouth. It began on the saying of the code phrase \"This meeting\ncan do nothing further to save the country\" by Samuel Adams. For 10 points, name this 1773\nincident in which the Sons of Liberty dressed as Mohawks and destroyed British goods.",
      "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "The introduction of copper plating caused incidents of this kind named for Spithead and Nore.\nFletcher Christian led another event of this kind, which caused a new population to settle on\nPitcairn Island and opposed William Bligh. For 10 points, name these events in British history in\nwhich the crew of a ship rebelled against the captain, as on the HMS Bounty.",
      "answer": "mutiny"
    },
    {
      "question": "This military leader was declared a martyr by Pope Callixtus III, a generation after this saint's\ncapture at Compiègne (pr. cahmp-YEN-yuh). Pierre Cauchon (pr. COO-shun) led the court\nwhich condemned her to be burned at the stake in 1431 following her relief of the siege of\nOrléans (pr. OH-lee-ahn). For 10 points, name this teenage French patriot of the Hundred Years\nWar.",
      "answer": [
        "Joan of Arc",
        "Jeanne d'Arc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The \"July Theses\" defined the Communist regime of what Eastern European country,\nwhose Ploiești (pr. ploy-ESH-tuh) oil fields were targeted by Operation Tidal Wave?",
      "answer": "Romania"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person was appointed as the head of an expedition to Scutari (pr. scoo-TAH-ree) by\nwar minister Sidney Herbert, who knew of her efforts to improve sanitation. She became known\nas the \"Lady with the Lamp\" for her efforts during the Crimean War. For 10 points, name this\n1850s British woman, the founder of modern nursing.",
      "answer": [
        "Florence Nightingale",
        "Nightingale"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When it became apparent that this event had failed, a disgusted Erich Ludendorff simply\nwalked away, leading its main organizer to be sentenced to the Landsberg, where Mein Kampf\nwas written. For 10 points, name this failed 1923 attempt by Adolf Hitler to seize power in\nGermany by leading an uprising at a Munich drinking venue.",
      "answer": "Beer Hall Putsch"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The \"condottiere\" (pr. cahn-DOE-tee-AIR-ee) were what type of soldiers, who fought\nmost of the wars of Renaissance Italy and were often of English origin and whose use was\nwarned against by Machiavelli?",
      "answer": "mercenaries"
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician controversially claimed that this place is not independent due to \"money and\nethnic votes.\" This place was to be recognized as a \"distinct society\" in a failed 1987\namendment block, the Meech Lake Accord. This place rejected independence by a narrow\nmargin in a 1995 referendum. For 10 points, name this French-speaking Canadian province.",
      "answer": "Quebec"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Todor Zhivkov was the longtime Communist dictator of what Eastern European\ncountry, which used ricin pellets fired out of a modified umbrella to assassinate dissidents, and\nroughly corresponds to ancient Thrace?",
      "answer": "Bulgaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man advocated for a “priesthood of all believers” in the work To the Christian Nobility of the\nGerman Nation. He was protected by Frederick the Wise after Charles V ordered his arrest. Pope Leo X\nexcommunicated this man with the bull Exsurge Domine [EX-ur-gay DOE-mee-nay] after he posted the\n95 Theses. For ten points, name this German priest who began the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": [
        "Martin Luther",
        "Luther"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler attempted to establish the Kingdom of Livonia as a vassal state, and this ruler established\nhis country’s first printing press at Kitai-gorod. This ruler conquered Kazan and Astrakhan, and he\nestablished a secret police force known as the Oprichniki. Feodor I succeeded this ruler after he killed his\neldest son in a fit of rage, eventually leading to the Time of Troubles. For ten points, name this first Tsar\nof Russia whose epithet notes his power, not his cruelty.",
      "answer": [
        "Ivan IV of Russia",
        "Ivan IV",
        "Ivan the Terrible",
        "Ivan Grozny"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The War of Jenkins’ Ear was part of what larger conflict over succession to a European\nthrone?",
      "answer": [
        "War of the Austrian Succession",
        "Austrian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The aftermath of this event led to the creation of the Quadruple Alliance and the formation of the 38\nstate German Confederation. It restored the Bourbon Dynasty in France with Louis XVIII. This meeting\nwas interrupted by the Hundred Days and it was headed by Austrian minister Klemens von Metternich.\nFor ten points, name this 1815 meeting that sought to organize post-Napoleonic Europe.",
      "answer": "Congress of Vienna"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gave the Appeal of 18 June Speech during one war. This leader’s opposition to the European\nCommission led to the Empty Chair Crisis. He was later criticized after Expo 67 for proclaiming “Long\nlive free Quebec!” This man’s government ended a conflict with the FLN by signing the Evian Accords.\nHe was brought to power in the May Crisis, leading to the formation of the Fifth Republic. For ten points,\nname this French Prime Minister who led the Free French Forces during WWII.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles de Gaulle",
        "Gaulle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This family’s crest pictures a red cow eating grass against a yellow background. One member of this\nfamily hosted an orgy in the Banquet of the Chestnuts. That man, the enemy of Girolamo Savonarola,\nhad formed the League of Venice to oppose Charles VIII’s invasion of Italy. That man’s son had embarked\non the Romagna campaign, and was the inspiration for Niccolo Machiavelli’s The Prince. For ten points,\nname this Italian family whose members included Cesare and Pope Alexander VI.",
      "answer": [
        "Borgia family",
        "Borgia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this battle, Major Sylvain-Raynal managed to defend Fort Vaux for over a week, but the lightly\ndefended Fort Douaumont [DOO-oh-MOHN] was captured without a fight. General Nivelle issued the\norder “they shall not pass” during this battle, and General Falkenhyn sought to “bleed France white”\nin this battle. For ten points, name this extremely bloody 9-month-long battle during World War I at a\nFrench fortress town.",
      "answer": "Verdun"
    },
    {
      "question": "One side’s attack on Saarbrucken early in this war showed the value of their Chassepot [sha-say-poh]\nrifles, but was defeated at the Battle of Wissembourg [VISS-em-boorg]. The Army of Chalons was formed\nduring this war to rescue troops encircled at Metz, and this war was ended by the Treaty of Frankfurt.\nThe Second Empire was dissolved after a defeat at Sedan in this war. For ten points, name this war that\nresulted in the formation of the German Empire and the defeat of Napoleon III.",
      "answer": [
        "Franco-Prussian War",
        "Franco-Prussian",
        "Franco-German War",
        "Franco-German",
        "War of 1870"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader bribed journalists with the Reptile Fund. His education minister, Adalbert Falk,\nadministered the May Laws, and he called a conference to modify the Treaty of San Stefano. He also\ncalled another conference of the same name, which incited the Scramble for Africa. This man sent the Ems\ndispatch to spark war against France, which resulted in his forming a unified country under the Prussian\nmonarch Wilhelm I. For ten points, name this Chancellor who unified Germany.",
      "answer": [
        "Otto von Bismarck",
        "Bismarck"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler faced early trouble from two Eberhards, of Bavaria and Franconia, and his half-brother\nThankmar during his early reign. Liudolf, this man’s son, fought against him before a notable battle, and\nJohn XII crowned this man before being deposed by this ruler. This son of Henry the Fowler was aided by\nConrad the Red to defeat the Magyars at the Battle of Lechfeld. For ten points, name this Saxon German\nking, the first Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Otto I",
        "Otto the Great",
        "Otto"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s wife, Katharina von Bora, was forced to evacuate the Black Cloister during the\nSchmalkaldic War. This man received the protection of Frederick III of Saxony and debated Zwingli in\nthe Marburg Colloquy. This critic of Johann Tetzel was excommunicated at the Diet of Worms after\nprotesting the sale of indulgences on the door of Wittenberg Cathedral. For ten points, name this German\nmonk whose Ninety-Five Theses started the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": [
        "Martin Luther",
        "Luther"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man exiled a rival to Compiegne after she tried to have this man dismissed in the Day\nof the Dupes. This rival of Marie de Medici and founder of the Academie Francaise engineered the siege of La Rochelle and French participation in the Thirty Years’ War, and was known as the “Red Eminence”. For ten points, name this cardinal and chief minister to Louis XIII.",
      "answer": [
        "Cardinal Richelieu",
        "Richelieu",
        "Armand Jean du Plessis",
        "du Plessis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This plant arrived in the New World thanks to Beatriz de Bobadilla, who gave cuttings of it to\nChristopher Columbus. Boiling houses converted the juice of this plant into a raw material that could\nthen be shaped into a loaf. In the late 18th century, the beet provided a European-based replacement for\nthis crop, which was grown by slave-based plantations throughout the Caribbean. For ten points, name\nthis grass crop that produces stalks rich in sucrose that can be refined into a popular sweetener.",
      "answer": [
        "sugarcane",
        "sugar cane"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man consolidated his power when his rival Harry von Arnim was caught pilfering secret\ngovernment records. This leader provoked a war in which his nation gained Alsace-Lorraine after the\nbattles of Sedan and Metz. Leo von Caprivi succeeded this editor of the Ems Dispatch, who espoused the\npolicy of realpolitik [real-pol-ih-teek] in the “Blood and Iron” speech. For ten points, name this instigator\nof the Franco-Prussian War, an “Iron Chancellor” credited with unifying the German states.",
      "answer": [
        "Otto von Bismarck",
        "Bismarck"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This war’s French theater included a victory for the Duc d’Enghien [”duke” don-GYEN] at the Battle\nof Rocroi [roh-CWAH]. The Bohemian phase of this war ended with the Battle of White Mountain and\nthe defeat of the Winter King. Wallenstein and the Count of Tilly served as Imperial generals during this\nwar, in which Gustavus Adolphus was killed. The Peace of Westphalia ended, for ten points, what war\nfought over religion in modern-day Germany that lasted from 1618 to 1648?",
      "answer": [
        "Thirty Years’ War",
        "Thirty Years"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This modern-day nation was dominated by the Chola Dynasty until its liberation by Vijayabahu I,\nwho re-established Buddhism. Its native Kingdom of Kandy was dominated by the Dutch and conquered\nby the British, who grew tea in their colony of Ceylon. The majority Sinhalese fought with the Tamil\nTigers on, for ten points, what island off the coast of India?",
      "answer": [
        "Sri Lanka",
        "Ceylon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler resolved territorial disputes with Nader Shah by signing the Treaty of Resht and failed to\nform an alliance with William III. This man employed Patrick Gordon to capture Azov, which he later\ngave back to Ahmed III. He gave civil service a structured hierarchy via the Table of Ranks as part of an\neffort to reform the bureaucracy, and he disbanded the streltsy. The boyars lost both political power and\ntheir beards under the reign of, for ten points, what “Great” modernizing tsar of Russia?",
      "answer": [
        "Peter the Great",
        "Peter I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this war, Hanover was forced to withdraw after the Convention of Klosterzeven, then re-entered\nafter the Battle of Rossbach. The Diplomatic Revolution led to the setup of this war’s alliances. This war\nwas motivated in part by an Austrian desire to recover Silesia. It began with an invasion of Saxony and\nended with the Treaty of Paris between Britain and France. For ten points, name this global war between\nEuropean powers that ended in 1763, often considered the first “World War” for its theaters in North\nAmerica and India.",
      "answer": [
        "Seven Years’ War",
        "Seven Years"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man competed with Christopher Columbus’ unhappy son as the governor of Puerto Rico. In\n1521, this man was mortally wounded in a skirmish with the Caloosahatchee by a poisoned arrow; his\nmen sailed him to Havana, where he died. For ten points, name this Spanish explorer, the first European\nto set foot in the modern United States, whose 16th century travels in Florida did not find the Fountain\nof Youth.",
      "answer": [
        "Juan Ponce de Leon",
        "Ponce de Leon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man is in the center of a mosaic in the Basilica of San Vitale in Ravenna, which was conquered\nby the man to his right in that mosaic. The first appearance of Yersinia pestis in Europe occurred during\na plague named for this man. Belisarius conquered the Vandals for this ruler, whose reign was described\nin Procopius’s Secret History. The Nika Riots opposed this husband of Theodora. For ten points, name\nthis Byzantine emperor who published a law code in 529 AD.",
      "answer": [
        "Justinian I",
        "Justinian",
        "Justinian the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Anif Document ended centuries of Wittelsbach rule in this state. Prussia and Austria fought\nover this state in a war of succession known as the Potato War. This state, which fought with Napoleonic\nFrance against its eastern neighbor, Austria, was once ruled by Ludwig the Mad, who built the castle\nof Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-shtein]. For ten points, name this primarily Catholic state in southern\nGermany whose capital is Munich.",
      "answer": [
        "Bavaria",
        "Bayern"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this program was given the call sign “Chaika,” or “Seagull,” and completed her\nintended action 48 times. The exclamation “poyekhali!” was made at the start of one of this program’s\nmissions; that mission, which began at the Baikonur Cosmodrome, was Vostok 1 and launched in 1961.\nValentina Tereshkova and Yuri Gagarin were members of, for ten points, what Cold War-era program\nthat, in 1957, launched Sputnik into orbit?",
      "answer": [
        "Soviet Union’s space program",
        "Soviet space",
        "Soviet space program",
        "Kosmicheskaya programma SSSR",
        "Russian space program",
        "Russia space",
        "Russia space program"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This group secured power in Chelmno Land after its natives agreed to the Treaty of Christburg. This group expanded operations in Prussia at the request of Konrad of Masovia. This group failed to take Pskov from Alexander Nevsky after being defeated on Lake Peipus in the Battle of the Ice. The influence of this group declined after losing at Grunwald to Poland-Lithuania. For ten points, name this group of German crusaders.",
      "answer": [
        "Teutonic Order or Teutonic Knights",
        "Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The towns of Hastings and Rye received tax exemptions in exchange for maintaining these objects as part of a group of five protected cities. Sutton Hoo is the site of a buried, undisturbed one of these objects from the 7th century. Henry I’s son William Adelin was killed in a disaster involving one of these vehicles, which were used during raids on English monasteries. For ten points, name these vehicles built in Southampton and other English port cities.",
      "answer": [
        "ships",
        "boats",
        "longship after Sutton Hoo is said"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Two answers required. A conflict between these two countries was sparked by the destruction of a\nbakery owned by a man named Remontel. Maximilian I was installed by one of these countries on the\nthrone of the other. Ignacio Zaragoza led one of these two countries in victory against the other at the\nBattle of Puebla, which is commemorated by Cinco de Mayo. For ten points, name these two countries\nthat clashed under leaders like Porfirio Diaz and Napoleon III.",
      "answer": "Mexico and France"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. This event was briefly halted when a nearby patrol forced William Dawes to\nflee; he subsequently fell off his horse and could not finish his mission. This event’s central participant\nslipped by the Somerset by boat after Robert Newman had placed two lanterns in the Old North Church.\nMilitia were able to prepare to fight at Lexington and Concord thanks to, for ten points, what event in\nwhich a Boston silversmith warned of approaching British soldiers?",
      "answer": [
        "Paul Revere’s midnight ride",
        "Revere ride",
        "Revere's midnight ride"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, heavy fighting took place near Papelotte and La Haye Sainte. Michel Ney led a\nfailed cavalry charge against the British during this battle, where the British Foot guards repelled an\nattack by the French Imperial Guard, their first defeat. The arrival of the Prussian army under Blucher\nswung the tide in, for ten points, what 1815 victory for the Duke of Wellington, the last major battle of\nthe Napoleonic Wars?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Waterloo",
        "Waterloo"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A depiction of this event dubbed a customs office as “Butcher’s Hall;” Henry Pelham created that\nengraving. During this event, Richard Palmes attacked Thomas Preston with a club, prompting a volley\nof gunfire that killed Crispus Attucks. John Adams controversially agreed to defend a group of British\nsoldiers accused of murder for their roles in this event. For ten points, name this 1770 killing of five\nprotesters in Massachusetts.",
      "answer": [
        "Boston Massacre",
        "the Incident on King Street"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s regent, Sophia Alekseyevna, listened to his meetings through a hole in his throne and led a revolt that forced this leader to disband the Streltsy. This man learned Dutch shipbuilding techniques on his “Great Embassy” tour of Europe. He reorganized the Table of Ranks to weaken the Boyars, and he taxed long beards as part of his reform efforts. For ten points, name this westernizing Russian tsar.",
      "answer": "Peter the Great or Peter I"
    },
    {
      "question": "At age 21, this man founded a group modeled on English coffeehouses called the Junto. After partnering with Hugh Meredith, this man founded a short-lived publication that was the first German language paper in America. In an essay titled The Way of Wealth, this man claimed that “There are no gains without pains,” one of many maxims collected in an annual series that ran from 1732 to 1758 under the name Poor Richard’s Almanac. For ten points, name this Founding Father on the $100 bill.",
      "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Physicists often use the “Left step” alternative to this system; another famous alternative was created by Theodor Benfey in a spiral shape. The most recent change to this system included an addition named for the state of Tennessee. This system initially had blank spaces left for “eka-germanium” and other undiscovered entries. Dmitri Mendeleev introduced, for ten points, what system that organizes the 118 chemical elements?",
      "answer": "periodic table of the elements"
    },
    {
      "question": "After they were slow in pledging their allegiance to this king, the MacDonald Clan were massacred in Glencoe. Upon taking the throne, this king was read the Declaration of Right by Parliament; that later became part of the English Bill of Rights. This King’s forces defeated James II’s Jacobite uprising at the Battle of the Boyne, after which this Dutch stadtholder assumed power in the Glorious Revolution. For ten points, name this husband of Mary II, a Prince of Orange and 17th century king of England.",
      "answer": "William III of England or William of Orange,"
    },
    {
      "question": "A series of Reflections on this period were written by Edmund Burke. During this period, the seating arrangements in the National Assembly gave rise to the modern left-right political spectrum. This period led to the execution of thousands of Monarchists and Girondins during the Reign of Terror. Maximilien Robespierre came to prominence during, for ten points, what period of French history that toppled the monarchy?",
      "answer": "French Revolution"
    },
    {
      "question": "A banker and a judge who helped draft this treaty were nicknamed the “heavenly twins.” Polish pianist Ignacy Paderewski served as a delegate to this treaty, which left the status of the Teschen district unresolved and demanded the transfer of the regions of Eupen-Malmedy and Saar. This treaty was supervised by the “Big Four”, including Vittorio Orlando, Georges Clemenceau, and David Lloyd George. For ten points, name this peace treaty with Germany that ended World War I.",
      "answer": "Treaty of Versailles"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tacitus recorded that, before this leader’s uprising, a statue of Victory fell down, as if turning its back in retreat. Due to the Roman governor’s absence at Mona, this leader trounced the Ninth Legion and destroyed a temple dedicated to Claudius. Suetonius defeated this ruler’s forces at the Battle of Watling Street. Camulodunum and Londinium were destroyed by an army of Britons led by, for ten points, what British warrior queen of the Iceni?",
      "answer": [
        "Boudica",
        "Boadicea"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was preceded by an engagement at Flirey that allowed one side to take control of local railway lines. Fort Vaux and Douamount were heavily contested in this battle. Erich von Falkenhayn was dismissed for failing to win this battle, despite his boast that he would bleed his enemies white. Philippe Petain led French troops to victory in, for ten points, what lengthy 1916 battle for a French fortress city?",
      "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this group in Shanghai organized a seven-day camp at the Moganshan resort. The motto “Blood and Honor” was adopted by this group, which was led by Baldur von Schirach and Artur Axmann. Volkssturm commonly drafted members of this group, one unit of which assisted the Kriegsmarine. An organization similar to this one that was only open to women was the League of German Girls. For ten points, name this organization consisting of boys who assisted the Nazi effort.",
      "answer": [
        "Hitler Youth",
        "Hitlerjugend"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, Lord Salisbury held a “khaki election” named for the newly-introduced army uniforms. Sir Arthur Conan Doyle volunteered as a doctor in this war, in which Robert Baden Powell outlasted a 217-day siege at Mafeking. The all-women Fawcett Commission investigated the British use of concentration camps in this war, which was incited by Leander Starr Jameson’s raid. For ten points, name this turn of the 20th-century war between Britain and Dutch Afrikaners.",
      "answer": "Second Boer War"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle’s winners opened fire on William Stevenson’s friendly unit when it insisted on retreating to Helpmekaar. Members of John Chard’s engineers were caught in this battle after they were dispatched to repair pontoon bridges on the Buffalo River. Eleven Victoria Crosses were awarded for this battle, the most ever given to a single regiment. This battle’s winners defended a hospital building on the same day that the Battle of Isandlwana was fought. For ten points, name this 1879 battle in which 100 British troops repelled a Zulu impi.",
      "answer": "Battle of Rorke’s Drift"
    },
    {
      "question": "Henry Pelham created a depiction of this event titled The Fruits of Arbitrary Power. John Adams declared that “facts are stubborn things” while successfully defending the perpetrators of this event. In Paul Revere’s depiction of this event, Thomas Preston is shown deliberately ordering an attack on a gathered crowd. Crispus Attucks was killed in, for ten points, what 1770 event in which British soldiers fired on civilians in Massachusetts?",
      "answer": [
        "Boston Massacre",
        "Incident on King Street"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Louis XV demanded that this monarch renounce Francis I’s claims to the Duchy of Lorraine in favor of the deposed Stanislaw I of Poland. In the Treaty of Aachen, this monarch was forced to cede Parma to Bourbon Spain. This daughter of Charles VI fought a war with Frederick II which resulted in Prussia seizing control of Silesia. The Pragmatic Sanction of 1713 allowed the ascension of, for ten points, what Empress of Austria?",
      "answer": "Empress Maria Theresa"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man expressed his desire that “poisonous envenomed worms” be drafted into forced labor, and demanded synagogues be burned to the ground in his On the Jews and their Lies. Frederick III kidnapped this man and held him in Wartburg Castle to protect him from the Holy Roman Emperor. In Exsurge Domine, Leo X threatened this man with excommunication if he didn’t recant his beliefs. For ten points, name this former German friar who created the 95 Theses.",
      "answer": "Martin Luther"
    },
    {
      "question": "This political party’s principles were outlined in the Tamworth Manifesto, written by Robert Peel as a way to separate his policies from those of his ally, the Duke of Wellington. A modern leader of this party took power after the “Winter of Discontent,” replacing James Callaghan in 1979. For ten points, name this British political party whose members, like Margaret Thatcher, are commonly known as “Tories.”",
      "answer": "Conservative and Unionist Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the ground portion of this campaign, the London Irish Rifles captured four soldiers in the Battle of the Graveney Marsh. The failure of this campaign led one side to cancel Operation Sea Lion, a planned amphibious invasion. In response to this campaign, Winston Churchill praised the pilots of the Royal Air Force. The Blitz attacks on London followed, for ten points, what air campaign against Great Britain carried out by Nazi Germany?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Britain",
        "The Air Battle for England",
        "Luftschlacht um England"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1944, this man reached “ace in a day” status by, in part, scaring a German pilot into crashing into his wingman. Two nights before his most famous feat, this man broke two ribs riding horses but only told his wife and friend Jack Ridley. This man, who named his plane Glamorous Glennis after his wife, was dropped out of the bomb bay of a B-29 bomber in the experimental Bell X-1 in 1947. For ten points, name this first pilot to break the sound barrier.",
      "answer": "Charles Elwood “Chuck” Yeager"
    },
    {
      "question": "Much of this battle took place at the Chalmette Plantation. Alexander Cochrane helped the losing side in this battle, which led to a siege of Fort St. Phillip. Edward Pakenham led the British in this battle against an army aided by the pirate Jean Lafitte. This battle took place two weeks after the Treaty of Ghent was signed. For ten points, name this victory for Andrew Jackson during the War of 1812, a defense of the most populous city in Louisiana.",
      "answer": "Battle of New Orleans"
    },
    {
      "question": "This monarch introduced religious freedom in his kingdom with the Declaration of Indulgence, which was partially meant to protect his own Catholicism. George Jeffreys was appointed by this man to severely punish the instigators of the Monmouth Rebellion in the Bloody Assizes. This successor of Charles II served as the Stuart king before being replaced by the House of Orange. For ten points, name this King of England overthrown in the Glorious Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "James II of England",
        "James VI of Scotland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Production of these works was suspended during World War II until 1944, when the Allies requested a reprint of its 1939 French issue for its highly detailed maps. This publication ignored Los Angeles for a decade until 2019, when it released an updated California edition; that work cited seven locations, including The French Laundry by Thomas Keller, as “worth a special detour,” its highest rating. For ten points, name this red-covered guide that awards up to three stars to exceptional restaurants and was originally intended to increase sales for its namesake tire company.",
      "answer": "Michelin Guides"
    },
    {
      "question": "Joseph Warren was killed at this battle as one side retreated across Charlestown Neck after running out of gunpowder, leaving their opponents with a Pyrrhic victory. During this battle, Israel Putnam allegedly ordered his troops not to fire until they saw the whites of their enemies’ eyes as British troops stormed a redoubt on Breed’s Hill. For ten points, name this Boston-area battle that followed Lexington and Concord.",
      "answer": "Battle of Bunker Hill A"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Tamworth Manifesto outlined the ideals of this modern political party. One prime minister from this party was a rival of William Gladstone and made Queen Victoria the “Empress of India.” Another prime minister from this party repealed the Corn Laws. This political party’s leaders included Benjamin Disraeli and founder Robert Peel. For ten points, name this British political party, sometimes called the Tories, that traditionally stands opposed to the Liberals and Labour.",
      "answer": "Conservative Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler survived an assassination attempt by Giuseppe Fieschi. Early in his life, this ruler fled to Austria with Charles Dumouriez. This monarch’s reign saw the death of Jean Lamarque result in the June Rebellion, and his foreign minister was Francois Guizot. This monarch rose to power during the July Revolution of 1830 that deposed Charles X, and was succeeded by Napoleon III. For ten points, name this citizen king of France.",
      "answer": "Louis Philippe I"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler’s navy fought off one attack by using fireships to thwart enemies at the battle of Gravelines [grav-LEEN]. One of this ruler’s admirals launched a daring raid on Cadiz, boasting he had “singed the beard” of a rival king. This patron of Francis Drake gave the Tilbury speech, where this ruler declared she had the “heart and stomach of a king” in the face of invasion from the Spanish Armada. For ten points, name this daughter of Henry VIII, the “virgin queen” of England. D",
      "answer": "Elizabeth I"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man deployed the Blue Division to fight in Russia and created the National Movement as part of a corporatist state. In the Ifni War this man lost territory in the Sahara to Morocco, although he refused to cede Ceuta and Melilla. He chose Juan Carlos I as his successor and avoided joining Hitler during World War Two, averting war with Britain by not attacking Gibraltar. For ten points, name this Generalissimo and longtime dictator of Spain.",
      "answer": "Francisco Franco D"
    },
    {
      "question": "This university's plan may have been based on that of a failed attempt to create another university at Henricus seventy years prior. The first Greek letter society, Phi Beta Kappa, originated at this university in 1776. The missionary James Blair founded this university, whose students were originally required to declare their belief in the Thirty-Nine Articles, as this university was an Anglican institution at the time. Founded in 1693, this university was advocated for by the House of Burgesses. For ten points, name this university in Williamsburg, Virginia named for two British monarchs.",
      "answer": "The College of William and Mary in Virginia"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a child, this ruler almost drowned in a pond after his mother, Anne of Austria, left him unsupervised. This ruler removed protections for Huguenots in France by revoking the Edict of Nantes. This ruler lost both the War of Devolution and the War of Spanish Succession and ruled with Cardinal Mazarin as his advisor. This ruler built the Palace of Versailles and once said “I am the state.” For ten points, name this longest-reigning French monarch known as the “Sun King.”",
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event ended when acting governor Thomas Hutchison promised a fair investigation into this event if the crowd watching the event dispersed. This event is depicted in a famous engraving by Paul Revere. John Adams defended eight soldiers involved in this event that led to the death of a black dockworker named Crispus Attucks. For ten points, name this 1770 event in which British soldiers fired on a crowd, killing five unarmed citizens in the capital of Massachusetts.",
      "answer": "Boston Massacre A"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person served in the Auxiliary Territorial Service during World War Two and was harshly criticized for being “out of touch” by John Grigg after the Suez Crisis. The term “annus horribilis” was used by this figure to describe a year in which two of her three children’s marriages ended and a fire broke out in Windsor Castle. This figure’s eldest child separated from his spouse due to Camilla Parker-Bowles. That son was Charles, the Prince of Wales. For ten points, name this longest reigning British monarch.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth II T"
    },
    {
      "question": "Support for this event gained traction when Albert Wedemeyer was able to apply his experiences traveling from India to China via the Himalayas. Logistics for this event were supplied by Brian Robertson to General Lucius Clay. Gail Halvorsen became known as the “candy bomber” during this event, the U.S. portion of which was codenamed Operation Vittles. 4,500 tons of cargo were delivered daily at this event’s heiRght. For ten points, name this 1948 event in which the Western Allies circumvented a Soviet blockade in Germany.",
      "answer": "Berlin Airlift"
    },
    {
      "question": "A character in this short story passes British spy Major Andre’s tree and loses his horse Gunpowder’s saddle after a party in Tarry Town. In this story, Katrina Van Tassel marries Brom Bones, who laughs when a crushed pumpkin is found near where a schoolteacher, Ichabod Crane, has vanished while being chased by a Galloping Hessian. For ten points, name this short story by Washington Irving in which the title location is haunted by the Headless Horseman.",
      "answer": "\"The Legend of Sleepy Hollow\""
    },
    {
      "question": "A loan from this nation's Erlanger & Co. allowed the Confederacy to build ironclads as blockade runners. Three emissaries from this nation requested bribes from U.S. diplomats before allowing negotiations with Talleyrand in the XYZ Affair. The U.S. fought the Quasi-War with this nation, who earlier sent armed forces to the Thirteen Colonies during the Yorktown campaign. The Louisiana colony was sold to the United States by, for ten points, what European country?",
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of France or Royaume de France",
        "Republic of France",
        "or French First Republic",
        "or République Française"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The northern half of this peninsula was controlled in the 600s by an Exarchate [[EKS-ar-kate]] based in Ravenna. Hannibal Barca crossed the Alps with a mercenary army to raid this peninsula which hosts several microstates, including San Marino and Vatican City. For ten points, name this peninsula, the former home of the Etruscan civilization and the heart of the Roman Empire. ANSWER:ItalianPeninsula (acceptItalicPeninsula;acceptApenninePeninsula before \"Apennine\" is mentioned; acceptItaly) (2) This leader obtained a doctorate in quantum chemistry in 1986 prior to entering politics. This politician played a central role in negotiating the Treaty of Lisbon and was a main figure behind the stimulus plan to help shelter the European Union from the Great Recession. The leader of the Christian Democratic Union from 2000 to 2018, this politician was elected to her highestpositionin2005.Fortenpoints,namethisfirstfemalechancellor of Germany.",
      "answer": [
        "AngelaMerkelor Angela DorotheaMerkel",
        "Angela DorotheaKasner"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler called Foreign Minister Nikita Panin a \"personal encyclopedia,\" though Panin fell out of favor byadvocatingfortheNorthernAlliancewithPrussia.Toconvincethis empress that the typical serf fares well, herloverandadvisorGrigoryPotemkinsupposedly showed her retinue false villages in Crimea. Upon conversion to the Russian Orthodox church, the name Yekaterina wasgivento,fortenpoints,whichRussianempressofthe18th century? ANSWER:Catherinethe Great (acceptCatherineII;acceptYekaterinaII before mentioned) (6) The \"Plan of the Three Guarantees\" in this nation's city of Iguala established a short-lived Constitutional Monarchythere.Theransackingofaforeignchef'sshopledtothe First French Intervention in this nation during the Pastry War. This nation's war of independence began after the Grito de Dolores by Don Miguel Hidalgo. Much of New Spain was made up of, for ten points, what North American nation to the south of the United States?",
      "answer": [
        "United States ofMexicoor Estados UnidosMexicanos",
        "acceptEUM",
        "First MexicanEmpire",
        "FirstMexicanRepublic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Troops preparing to confront this force were told \"I have the heart and stomach of a king\" by their leader at Tilbury. This force was commanded by the Duke of Medina Sidonia and lost at the Battle of Gravelines [[grahv-LEEN]]. Sir Francis Drake helped defeat this force shortly after he attacked Cádiz to \"singe the beard of\" its nation's ruler, Philip II. For ten points, name this fleet of ships sent by Spain in 1588 in an attempt to conquer England.",
      "answer": [
        "Spanish Armada or Grande y Felicísima Armada",
        "the Great and Most Fortunate Navy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Comparing it to the French conquest of Algeria, this act was promoted by Charles Sumner in asenatebill.Inapoliticalcartooncriticizingthisevent,amanmeanttorepresent Andrew Johnson lugs around an iceberg in a wheelbarrow. In an effort to avoid British conquest, Tsar Alexander II sent the diplomat Eduard de Stoeckl [[SHTEH-kul]] to execute this sale. For ten points, name this acquisition of a former Russian colony known to detractors as \"Seward's Folly.\"",
      "answer": [
        "U.S.PurchaseofAlaska",
        "answers whichreferenceBuyingAlaska 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Future Israeli prime minister Menachem Begin [[meh-NAH-kem BEH-gin]] sent a parcel bomb meant to kill this nation's head of state, instead killing police officer Karl Reichert [[\"RYE\"-kert]]. This state's \"EconomicMiracle\"wasorchestratedbyLudwigErhard [[EHR-hard]] and Chancellor Konrad Adenauer [[AH-den-ow-uh]]. Fortenpoints,namethis country, sometimes known as the \"Bonn Republic,\" which reunified with an eastern communist neighbor in 1990. ANSWER:West Germany(orWest Deutschland; acceptFederal Republic of Germany; or Bundesrepublik Deutschland; acceptFRG; orBRD; donot accept or prompt on \"Deutschland\" or \"Germany\") (8) This politician hired education reformer John Dewey, who suggested switching his country's alphabet to a Latin script. In 1924, this politician formally abolished the last recognized caliph, Abdulmejid II.Followingthisman'sfailuretogettheLeagueofNationsto annul the Treaty of Sèvres [[SEH-vruh]], this head of the Ankara government launched an invasion of the Greek zone of occupation. The father of modern Turkey was, for ten points, which 20th century politician?",
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa KemalAtatürkor Mustafa KemalPasha",
        "Ali Riza ogluMustafa 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A memorial to honor soldiers killed while serving on these vessels was built by the WarGravesCommission.ThefirsttimetheseweaponswereusedinWorldWarOneresulted in the sinking of the HMS Pathfinder. One ofthesevesselsunderthecommandofIronCross winner Otto Weddigen [[VEH-dih-gehn]] sank the so-called \"Live Bait Squadron\"inasingle hour. Fortenpoints,identifythesenavalsubmarinesoperatedbytheGermanEmpireduring the First and Second World Wars. ANSWER:U-Boats (acceptU-Boots; orUnterseeboots) (2) While in Paris, this man met with scientists Michel-Eugene Chevreul [[shev-RUHL]] and Ogdon Rood, who inspired his theories on the \"language of color.\" This developer of chromo-luminarism depicted the raucous Moulin Rouge [[moo-LAHN ROOZH]] in The Can-Can, and he was rejected from the Paris Salon after completing the massive Bathers at Asnières[/a] [[ahz-NYEHR]]. For ten points, name this French advocate of pointillism, on display in his [i]A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte[[ZHAHT]].",
      "answer": "Georges PierreSeurat"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man first came to prominence by suppressing the 13 Vendémiaire (pr. VON-deem-yair)\nrebellion with what Thomas Carlyle called \"a whiff of grapeshot.\" He made his brothers Joseph\nand Jerome into the kings of Spain and Westphalia, respectively. For 10 points, name this \"First\nCounsel\" who was defeated by the Duke of Wellington at Waterloo.",
        "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte, Napoleon, Napoleon I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napoleon was able to remove Austria and the Holy Roman Empire from the Third\nCoalition opposing him with what great 1805 victory in what is now the Czech Republic?",
        "answer": "Austerlitz, Battle of Austerlitz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Troops who carried out this action referred to it as “Blumenkrieg”, a term meaning \"war of\nflowers,\" because they were met by cheering crowds. Kurt Schuschnigg (pr. SHOOS-neg) was\nforced to resign to clear the way for this action, which began on March 11, 1938. For 10 points,\nidentify this forced incorporation of Austria into Nazi Germany.",
        "answer": "Anschluss"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Austria was forbidden from unifying with Germany by the Treaty of Saint-Germain\n(pr. sahn zhair-MON), which was signed at the end of what war?",
        "answer": "World War I, First World War, the Great War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's lavish spending on Italian art greatly expanded the Royal Collection. This man is\ndepicted with a stable boy, a horse, a walking stick, and red trousers, looking away from the\nThames (pr. TEMZ), in a portrait of him \"at the hunt.\" For 10 points, name this king whom\nAnthony van Dyck repeatedly painted prior to his execution in the English Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "Charles I of England",
          "Charles I"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other court painter made an insultingly realistic portrait of Charles IV of Spain\nand his family, as well as The Third of May, 1808?",
        "answer": [
          "Francisco Goya",
          "Francisco Jose de Goya y Lucientes",
          "Goya"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This device was originally named for doctor Antoine Louis. The \"tricoteuse\" (pr. TRICK-awtooz) were women who knitted next to this object. This object was used on up to forty thousand\npeople at the order of Maximilien Robespierre, who found himself subject to it in 1794. For 10\npoints, name this item which was used to execute Louis XVI and others during the French\nRevolution.",
        "answer": "guillotine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The guillotine was originally used to equalize execution methods for nobles and\nmembers of what group, the peasant section of France in the Estates-General?",
        "answer": [
          "Third Estate",
          "Third"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This queen came to the throne at age six, leading to the creation of a regency council\ndominated by Axel Oxenstierna (pr. OCK-sens-TURR-nuh). In 1654, this queen shocked\nEurope by abdicating her throne and converting to Catholicism, after which she lived out her life\nin Rome. For 10 points, name this daughter of Gustavus Adolphus, an “enlightened monarch” of\nSweden.",
        "answer": [
          "Queen Christina",
          "Christina"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Christina’s energetic studies with what philosopher of Discourse on Method, whom she\nsummoned to Sweden and often woke before dawn, are thought to have caused his death?",
        "answer": "Rene Descartes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A picket line formed by members of this profession got into a huge brawl with police at the\nBattle of Ogreave. Members of this profession who opposed the moderate NACODS joined the\nNUM led by Arthur Scargill. Members of this profession were dubbed \"the enemy within\" by\nMargaret Thatcher. For the point, identify this profession which launched a disastrous 1984\nBritish strike which closed down facilities for extracting bitumen.",
        "answer": [
          "coal miners"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which musical about a boy who wants to be a ballet dancer features a chorus of\ndisgruntled coal miners complaining about Margaret Thatcher?",
        "answer": "Billy Elliott"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this war, Lord Dundonald lifted the siege of Ladysmith. Lord Kitchener requested a group of\nAboriginal trackers to fight in this conflict, in which Winston Churchill was held as a prisoner of war and\ntensions were raised by the Jameson Raid. This war ended in the Treaty of Vereeniging, eight years before\nthe land was unified as South Africa. For ten points, name this 1899-1902 war in which the British ended\nthe Orange Free State.",
        "answer": [
          "Second Anglo-Boer War",
          "Anglo-Boer War",
          "Boer",
          "Second Boer War",
          "Boer War"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The term “Boer” referred to settlers who spoke this language that is descended from Dutch.",
        "answer": "Afrikaans"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Flight of the Wild Geese refers to one group of these people who left Ireland. Machiavelli praised\none type of them, although he considers them as useless as auxiliaries. Leaders of these in Italy were called\ncondottieri [con-doh-tee-AIR-ee], and the battle of Marignano saw the ascendancy of the Landsknecht\nover the most famous of these types of soldiers, who were recruited from their cantons and carried pikes.\nSwiss pikemen were, for ten points, what hired soldiers?",
        "answer": "mercenary"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Swiss mercenaries were most commonly hired by what nation, whose Francis I employed them\nat the battles of Marignano and Pavia?",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The inefficient Trabant was built in this former country. It used distinctive Ampelmannchen crosswalk\nsymbols that are now enjoyed as its modern residents experience “Ostalgie.” Its residents were once spied\non by the Markus Wolf-led Stasi, which revealed its records after reunification in 1990. For ten points,\nname this former Soviet-zone country with capital Berlin.",
        "answer": [
          "East Germany",
          "German Democratic Republic",
          "GDR",
          "Deutsche Demokratische Republik",
          "DDR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Oder-Neisse Line provided the border between East Germany and what other country?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Poland",
          "Poland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man fought during the Second Baron’s War against Simon de Montfort, who he killed at the\nBattle of Evesham. This monarch issued the Edict of Expulsion, which expelled all Jews from England.\nHe invaded Scotland, winning the Battle of Falkirk against the forces of William Wallace. For ten points,\nname this English King given the name “Longshanks” because of his height.",
        "answer": "Edward I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Edward I’s father Henry III was forced by the barons to agree to the Provisions of Oxford, which\nheavily influenced this later document that was signed by John I at Runnymede.",
        "answer": "Magna Carta"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “liquidators” dealt with the aftermath of this event, which was detected after a day in Forsmark,\nSweden. The Red Forest was created by this event, which led to a “zone of alienation” being marked\naround the city of Pripyat. It was triggered by a poorly-safeguarded experiment in which control rods\nwere manually removed, spreading radiation over much of Europe. For ten points, name this 1986 nuclear\nmeltdown in modern Ukraine.",
        "answer": [
          "Chernobyl nuclear disaster",
          "Chernobyl"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Chernobyl disaster was a major catalyst towards this Soviet premier’s adoption of glasnost,\na policy of openness and government transparency.",
        "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Three of this body’s first five acts dealt with Soviet occupation of Iran. Its operation is controversial,\nas the victorious Allied countries in World War II hold permanent member status and veto power, unlike\nin the General Assembly where non-binding resolutions are voted on. For ten points, name this 15-member\nbody that orders sanctions and peacekeeping operations for the United Nations.",
        "answer": [
          "United Nations Security Council",
          "Security Council"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This permanent member of the UN Security Council used the veto to oppose a criminal tribunal\ninvestigating the Malaysian Airlines disaster in Ukraine.",
        "answer": [
          "Russian Federation",
          "Russia"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Mitchel was sent to Bermuda as punishment for his writings about this event. During this event,\npeople called “soupers” converted to Protestantism in return for aid. The cottier system worsened this\nevent, in which the affected area received shipments of maize known as “Peel’s brimstone” and remained\na net food exporter to Britain. For ten points, over a million people starved in what event in which the\nstaple crop of an island west of Britain was ruined by blight?",
        "answer": [
          "Irish Potato Famine",
          "Great Famine",
          "Great Hunger"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In response to the Irish Potato Famine, Prime Minister Robert Peel repealed what set of tariffs\non imported grain in 1846?",
        "answer": "Corn Laws"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “X Article” in Foreign Affairs magazine coined this term; that article was written by George\nKennen, one of the “Wise Men” advocated this policy as a substitute for rollback. This policy was first\nperformed with the Truman Doctrine, which provided support to those resisting outside pressures. For ten\npoints, name this political and military poilcy, implemented by the U.S. during the Cold War to prevent\nthe spread of Communism abroad.",
        "answer": "Containment"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Containment was an alternative to this policy, French for “relaxation” and often described as\nthawing. It advocated for less hostile relations with the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": "Detente"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person’s childhood friend, the Princess de Lamballe, was murdered in the September Massacres.\nThe Carnation Plot attempted to save this monarch, a suspected lover of Axel Fersin. This monarch was\nwrongly blamed in the Diamond Necklace affair and was derisively called “the Austrian”. For ten points,\nname this Queen of France, who may have said “let them eat cake” and was guillotined after her husband\nLouis XVI.",
        "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Axel Fersin helped plan the escape of Marie Antoinette and Louis XVI from France, but they\nwere recognized at this small town near the border between Montmedy and Saint-Menehould.",
        "answer": "Varennes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler ignited a rebellion after appointing Yuri Dolgoruki to round up fugitive peasants in lands\nled by Kondraty Bulavin. This ruler signed the Treaty of Constantinople with Mustafa II, which led to\nthis ruler creating his country’s first navy base on the Sea of Azov. He instituted a beard tax for the\nboyars and traveled incognito to observe a Dutch shipyard as part of his Grand Embassy. For ten points,\nname this “great” Czar whose modernization included the founding of Saint Petersburg.",
        "answer": [
          "Peter I",
          "Peter the Great"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Peter I was a part of this Russian Dynasty which ruled Russia until the fall of Nicholas II.",
        "answer": [
          "Romanov dynasty",
          "Romanov"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This year saw the National Liberal party push Frederick VII to create a new constitution, which made\nhim share power with the Rigsdag. This year saw William O’Brien lead the Young Irelander Rebellion,\nand the March Revolution in this year in Germany led to the Frankfurt Assembly offering the German\ncrown to Wilhelm IV. Klemens von Metternich resigned as Chancellor of Austria in this year, which\nsaw the establishment of the French Second Republic. For ten points, name this year that saw multiple\nrevolutions against various European Governments.",
        "answer": "1848"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wilhelm IV was from this royal line that would rule Imperial Germany until the end of WW1.",
        "answer": [
          "Hohenzollern Dynasty",
          "Hohenzollern"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This king wrote the Defence of the Seven Sacraments attacking Martin Luther, for which he was\nrewarded with the title Defender of the Faith from Clement VII. This man, who passed the first Act\nof Supremacy and dissolved the monasteries, ordered his chief ministers Cardinal Wolsey and Thomas\nCromwell to arrange an annulment and marriage to Anne Boleyn. For ten points, name this King who\nfounded the Church of England so that he could divorce the first of his six wives.",
        "answer": [
          "Henry VIII Tudor",
          "Henry VIII"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry’s first, fifth, and sixth wives had this name. The first was a relative of Ferdinand and\nIsabella of Spain, the fifth was executed after sixteen months for adultery, and the last survived by\noutliving Henry.",
        "answer": "Catherine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An insurrection in this state was fought by the Milice. This state was the site of the Drancy\nconcentration camp. Its territory was known as a “free zone,” and it adopted the slogan “Work, Family,\nFatherland.” Prime Minister Pierre Laval led this state, which was able to scuttle its fleet in Toulon\nHarbor to prevent their re-occupiers from seizing the ships. For ten points, name this puppet government\nthat ruled part of France alongside Nazi Germany during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Vichy France",
          "Vichy",
          "French State"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Vichy France’s president was this World War I hero who led French forces at Verdun.",
        "answer": [
          "Henri-Philippe Petain",
          "Petain",
          "Philippe Petain"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, murderous mitrailleuse [mih-tray-uhs] and Chassepot [shass-poh] fire stalled one\nside’s attacks at the Battle of Gravelotte. After this war, Baden, Wurtemburg, and Bavaria joined a\ncountry that also gained Alsace-Lorraine through the Treaty of Frankfurt. This war ended shortly after\nthe losing leader was captured at the Battle of Sedan. For ten points, name this war in which Napoleon\nIII was soundly defeated by a state led by Otto von Bismarck.",
        "answer": [
          "Franco-Prussian War",
          "Franco-Prussian"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prussia was the first country to adopt the use of this material for making artillery, which helped\nit win the Franco-Prussian War. Krupp guns are made of this material.",
        "answer": "steel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Third Section was one of these organizations before it was succeeded by the Okhrana. Before\nhe held his highest post, Yuri Andropov was the head of one of these organizations. One of these\norganizations, the oprichniki, targeted the boyars and executed the Massacre of Novgorod. A feared one of\nthese during the Cold War was known as the Committee for State Security, or the KGB. For ten points,\nname these organizations that suppressed dissent in Russia.",
        "answer": [
          "Russian secret police",
          "secret police",
          "intelligence agencies",
          "intelligence"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Yuri Andropov’s tenure as head of the KGB, he advocated for the Soviet Union’s 1979\ninvasion of this country, often described as the USSR’s “Vietnam.”",
        "answer": [
          "Democratic Republic of Afghanistan",
          "Afghanistan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man rejected the occupation of the Philippines in his “Imperialism” speech. This frequent\nlecturer on the Chautauqua [sha-taw-kwa] circuit served as Secretary of State under Woodrow Wilson and\nwas the prosecutor in the Scopes Monkey Trial. At the the 1896 Democratic National Convention, this\npolitician called for free silver and shouted “You shall not crucify mankind.” For ten points, name this\nthree-time US presidential candidate who gave the Cross of Gold speech.",
        "answer": [
          "William Jennings Bryan",
          "Bryan"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bryan resigned as Secretary of State, unhappy with Wilson’s aggressive actions after the sinking\nof this British ocean liner by a German U-Boat in 1915.",
        "answer": [
          "RMS Lusitania",
          "Lusitania"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This war began with a failed invasion of the Danubian Principalities. One side in this war built the\nGreat Redan and a Malakoff redoubt to defend the city of Sevastopol. This war’s Battle of Balaclava\nincluded the heroism of the Thin Red Line and the disastrous Charge of the Light Brigade. Florence\nNightingale served as a medic in, for ten points, what war fought between by an Anglo-French alliance\nover a Russian peninsula in the Black Sea?",
        "answer": [
          "Crimean War",
          "Crimean"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Charge of the Light Brigade was an attempt to attack a formation of these weapons. The\nBritish captured a set of these weapons at Sevastopol, which were legendarily melted down for the steel\nused to make Victoria Cross medals.",
        "answer": [
          "cannons",
          "artillery"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Claims made about a social class in this work were later revised in its author’s Theories of Surplus\nValue. This work introduces the concept of historical materialism. A “holy alliance” created to “exorcise\nthis specter” is the focus of the first section of this work, which concludes by calling for the “workers of\nthe world” to “unite!.” For ten points, name this 1848 political pamphlet co-written by Friedrich Engels\nand Karl Marx.",
        "answer": "The Communist Manifesto"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marx’s idea that history repeats itself “first as tragedy, then as farce” was written about the\ncoup of this historical figure, the nephew of an earlier French dictator with a much more successful coup.",
        "answer": [
          "Napoleon III",
          "Louis-Napoleon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was able to lift trading restrictions after signing the Treaty of Kucuk Kaynarca [koo-chook\nkai-nar-ka]. This ruler descended from the royal family of Anhalt and founded the Hermitage. Cossacks\ntargeted this patron of Voltaire during Pugachev’s Rebellion. Fake villages to show prosperity were\nconstructed by this ruler’s lover, Grigory Potemkin. For ten points, name this enlightened despot and\n18th century Empress of Russia.",
        "answer": [
          "Catherine the Great",
          "Catherine II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Catherine the Great collaborated with Prussia and Austria in the first of three partitions of this\ncountry. This country would not become independent again until after World War I.",
        "answer": [
          "Poland-Lithuania",
          "Poland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s ruler was greatly embarrassed by the revelation of Philipp zu Eulenburg’s [oy-len-burg’s]\nhomosexuality. This country sent a gunboat to its rival’s territory in Morocco, causing the Agadir Crisis.\nIts high command was led by Helmuth von Moltke, and it was accused of sending the Zimmerman\nTelegram, causing the United States to declare war on this country. Kaisers led, for ten points, what\nmember of the Central Powers, an empire that invaded France during World War I?",
        "answer": [
          "Germany",
          "German Empire",
          "Second Reich",
          "Kaiserreich"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The early 20th century German empire held a naval arms race with the UK, consisting primarily\nof building these “all big gun” steam battleships. This class of ship was named for a British vessel.",
        "answer": "dreadnoughts"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "German saboteurs damaged this landmark in the 1916 Black Tom explosion. This structure’s\ncompletion was celebrated by the world’s first ticker-tape parade. It was built on what was then known\nas Bedloe’s Island, thanks in part to Joseph Pulitzer’s fundraising drive. This statue depicts a broken\nchain at the feet of a woman holding a tablet reading “July 4, 1776.” Frederic Bartholdi designed, for ten\npoints, what green-hued statue in New York Harbor?",
        "answer": "Statue of Liberty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What poem, written by Emma Lazarus to help raise money for the acquisition of the Statue of\nLiberty, states “Give me your tired, your poor, your huddled masses yearning to breathe free”?",
        "answer": "The New Colossus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two Partition Treaties were signed to prevent this war, while the Barrier Treaties allowed one of the\nvictors to set up a series of forts as a buffer. The capture of Port Royal in Acadia occurred in its North\nAmerican theater, which was called Queen Anne’s War. Great Britain gained Gibraltar after this war,\nduring which Marshal Tallard was crushed at the Battle of Blenheim [BLEN-um]. This war began after\nthe death of the childless Charles II and the proposed accession of Phillip of Anjou. For ten points, name\nthis war, ended by the Treaty of Utrecht, fought over the throne of the namesake Iberian nation.",
        "answer": [
          "War of the Spanish Succession",
          "Spanish Succession"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The military success of the alliance against France was mostly due to these two generals, who\nworked together at Blenheim and Malplaquet. Name either.",
        "answer": [
          "Eugene of Savoy",
          "Duke of Marlborough",
          "Marlborough",
          "John Churchill"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Citizens of this country, including Arthur Rudolph, were brought to the United States in Operation\nPaperclip. This country’s scientists developed a liquid-propellant engine for use in the first man-made\nobject to cross the Karman line into outer space; that object was used a “vengeance weapon” in 1944. For\nten points, name this country whose rocket scientists, including Werner Von Braun, developed the V-2\nrocket but did not create a nuclear weapon before it lost World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Nazi Germany",
          "Germany",
          "Third Reich"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Paperclip hid the Nazi backgrounds of the imported scientists, including Hubertus\nStrughold. Strughold had used human test subjects in his work at this German concentration camp near\nMunich, which the Americans used as a military base after the war.",
        "answer": "Dachau"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A civil war during this conflict was fought between the Armagnacs and Burgundians. One side of\nthis war sent out cavalry raids called chevauch´ees [sheh-voh-SHAYS], sometimes led by the Black Prince.\nCharles VII was crowned after this war’s Siege of Orleans was lifted. Longbows helped the English win\nthe Battle of Crecy during, for ten points, what war between England and France that lasted from 1337\nto 1453?",
        "answer": [
          "Hundred Years’ War",
          "Hundred Years’"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Siege of Orleans was lifted with the help of this 17-year-old French peasant girl. She was\ncaptured and burned at the stake by the English, but cleared by the Pope years later and made a saint in\n1920.",
        "answer": [
          "Saint Joan of Arc",
          "Joan of Arc",
          "Saint Jeanne d'Arc",
          "Jeanne d'Arc"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Carteret was given land in North Carolina and what is now this state by Charles II. The\nLoyalist William Franklin, son of Ben Franklin, governed this colony until the Revolution. In 1937, a dire\nradio report from this state noted flames “four or five hundred feet into the sky...Oh, the humanity!”\nThomas Edison’s Menlo Park labs were in, for ten points, what Atlantic coast state whose industrial cities\ninclude Newark and Trenton?",
        "answer": "New Jersey"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned 1937 radio report, including the cry “Oh, the humanity!”, detailed the fiery\ncrash of this German zeppelin.",
        "answer": [
          "LZ 129 Hindenburg",
          "Hindenburg"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Duringthiswar,theterm“khakielection,”wascoinedtodescribeanelectioninfluencedbyanongoing or finished war. The Fawcett Commission was formed after Emily Hobhouse reported on concentration camps used in this war. Prior to this war, Cecil Rhodes sponsored a failed attempt to trigger a settler uprising, the Jameson Raid. The British established control over the Orange Free State and the Transvaal in, for ten points, what South African war named for the defeated Dutch settlers?",
        "answer": "Second Boer War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the failure of the Jameson Raid, the leader of this country sent a congratulatory telegram to Paul Kruger, infuriating Britain. Queen Victoria later received an apology from this country’s leader, her grandson.",
        "answer": "Germany the leader being Kaiser Wilhelm II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1966, Secretary of State Dean Rusk asked this leader if a recent order applied to American soldiers\nin his country’s cemeteries. Lester Pearson noted that “Canadians do not need to be liberated” in his\ncriticism of this man’s declaration of “vive le Quebec libre.” This leader signed the Evian Accords, leading\nto the independence of Algeria. For ten points, name this first president of the Fifth Republic who led\nFree France in World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Charles de Gaulle",
          "de Gaulle"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1966, de Gaulle pulled France out of this organization’s Military Command Structure and\nordered foreign soldiers to leave France, leading to Rusk’s aforementioned question. France fully returned\nto this military alliance in 2009.",
        "answer": [
          "NATO",
          "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two answers required. These two countries fought the Battle of Pinkie, which became known as\n“Black Saturday” on the losing side. In the largest clash between these two countries, the invading side\nlost their king at Flodden Field. A queen of one of these countries was implicated in the Babington Plot\nand executed by the other’s queen, Elizabeth I. For ten points, name these two countries that were unified\nin 1707 and share a border on the isle of Great Britain.",
        "answer": "Scotland and England"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Battle of Flodden Field was instigated by Scotland, which invaded England\nto uphold its end of the Auld Alliance with this European country.",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "David Lloyd George and this man were the “Terrible Twins” of the People’s Budget. Harry Truman invited this man to speak at Westminster College, where he discussed the “sinews of peace” and described postwar Europe as being split by an “iron curtain.” This politician promised his people his “blood, toil, tears, and sweat” in his first speech as British Prime Minister. For ten points, name this leader of the UK during World War II.",
        "answer": "Sir Winston Leonard Spencer Churchill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Churchill replaced what fellow Conservative, who promised “peace for our time” after signing the Munich Agreement, as Prime Minister?",
        "answer": "Neville Chamberlain"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler failed to negotiate a trade agreement with Japan after storms blew a Japanese sea captain into this ruler’s territory. This ruler established the first publicly funded higher-education institution for women, the Smolny Institute. She eliminated required military service for the nobility and placed Stanislas Poniatowski, her former lover, on the throne of Poland in 1763. This ruler assumed power after a coup d’etat against her husband, Peter III. For ten points, name this “Great” Empress of Russia.",
        "answer": "Catherine the Great or Catherine II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Catherine’s scholarly patronage included support for this French playwright and philosopher, the chief editor of the Encyclop´edie.",
        "answer": "Denis Diderot"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This work ends by criticizing the “false security of peace,” citing Acts chapter 14, verse 22 for the idea that “tribulations” provide passage into heaven. Earlier, this document attacks the “human doctrine” that souls can “[fly] out of purgatory” after the payment of an indulgence; that attack is its 27th point. For ten points, name this document that was posted in Wittenburg in 1517 by Martin Luther, outlining his criticism of the Catholic Church in nearly 100 statements.",
        "answer": "95 Theses or Disputation on the Power of Indulgences"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Though the Theses don’t mention him by name, Luther’s criticism was largely aimed at this German preacher for his sale of indulgences for future sins.",
        "answer": "Johann Tetzel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was victorious at the Battle of Fontaine Francaise during a series of campaigns against Spain ended by the Treaty of Vervins. This man was finally named king as his rival lay dying from a fatal stabbing from Jacques Clement. Fran¸cois Ravaillac stabbed this man in the street in 1610, leading to Marie de’ Medici’s brief rule as regent for Louis XIII [thirteenth]. The Edict of Nantes [nahnt] was issued by, for ten points, what first Bourbon king of France?",
        "answer": [
          "Henry IV of France",
          "Henry of Navarre",
          "Henry III of Navarre"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry IV married Marie de’ Medici in 1600, shortly after annulling his marriage to this Valois princess. The wedding of Henry and this woman immediately preceded the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre.",
        "answer": "Margaret of Valois"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author of A History of the English-Speaking Peoples coined the term “special relationship.” This politician was replaced by Clement Attlee in a post-war election, then replaced Attlee six years later. One of this man’s speeches described offered his “blood, toil, tears, and sweat” to his country, and another proclaimed that an “Iron Curtain” had descended across Europe. For ten points, name this Prime Minister of Great Britain during World War II.",
        "answer": "Sir Winston Leonard Spencer-Churchill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Clement Attlee replaced Winston Churchill as Prime Minister when this party won the 1945 elections, the first time it had defeated the Conservatives.",
        "answer": "Labour Party"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Correspondence from this era of history is mapped in a digital project by Dan Edelstein called the Republic of Letters. Immanuel Kant held Frederick II as a ruler typical of this era in his essay “What is [the word that names this era].” A major project in this era comprised of over 70,000 articles; that work was partially compiled by d’Alembert and known as the Encyclopedie. Voltaire was a major figure of, for ten points, what philosophical era largely in the 18th century that challenged religious, social, and political establishments by stressing the use of reason?",
        "answer": [
          "Enlightenment",
          "le si`ecle des lumi`eres"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Frenchman worked with d’Alembert as the primary author of the Encyclopedie.",
        "answer": "Denis Diderot"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This Prime Minister oversaw the passing of the Great Reform Bill of William IV. This husband of Kitty Pakenham rose to prominence fighting the Tipu Sultan’s kingdom of Mysore. The Battle of Wavre helped prevent Emmanuel Grouchy from attacking this man, who received assistance from Gebhard von Blucher in his most famous battle in a Belgian town. For ten points, name this “Iron Duke,” the English commander who fought Napoleon at the Battle of Waterloo.",
        "answer": [
          "Arthur Wellesley, first Duke of Wellington",
          "either",
          "both underlined names"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before Waterloo, the Duke of Wellington’s English forces fought Napoleon in the Peninsular War on this European peninsula.",
        "answer": "Iberian Peninsula"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to legend, the losing side in this battle goaded the victors by sending them three tennis balls when they asked for gold. The winning side in this battle was forced to kill all its prisoners after an enemy raid on their baggage train. During this battle, wooden stakes driven into muddy ground rendered the losing side’s heavy cavalry useless. For ten points, name this battle fought on St. Crispin’s Day, 1415, in which the longbow secured an overwhelming English victory against France in the Hundred Years’ War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The English engaged the French at Agincourt while trying to reach Calais [ca-LAY], a city they controlled on the French shores of this body of water across from Dover.",
        "answer": "English Channel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this ruler’s coronation, a stampede led to the death of over a thousand people in the Khodynka Field tragedy. This man lost popularity after his forces opened fire on Father Gapon’s supporters outside the Winter Palace. After this ruler abdicated, he and his family were brought to Yekaterinburg, where they were executed in July 1918. The February Revolution ousted, for ten points, what final Tsar of Russia?",
        "answer": "Nicholas II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This daughter of Nicholas II was rumored to have survived the killing of the Romanov family, and imposters like Anna Anderson appeared over the ensuing years claiming to be her. DNA testing has since proven that this girl died in the attack.",
        "answer": "Anastasia Nikolaevna"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Wielbark culture of these people is the subject of Getica, a work by Jordanes. Emperor Valens died fighting these people, who were led by Fritigern, at the Battle of Adrianople. The 410 Sack of Rome was caused by Alaric, a leader of these people. Theodoric the Great led a kingdom of these people in Italy, while another group settled in Spain south of the Franks. For ten points, name this Germanic group that was split into Visi- and Ostro- branches.",
        "answer": [
          "Goths",
          "Visigoths and/or Ostrogoths"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The longest lasting community of the Goths was based in this peninsula, which is surrounded by the Sea of Azov and the Black Sea.",
        "answer": "Crimean Peninsula"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began when the promise of treasure from a chevauchee and seven years of peace was rendered undesirable by one side, whose troops were advised by William Douglas to attack without horses. The Captal de Buch masterminded a victorious flanking maneuver in this battle, which featured fighting by a young Philip the Bold. The Treaty of Bretigny was signed after this battle and granted three million gold crowns to its winning side. Edward the Black Prince won, for ten points, what 1356 battle during the Hundred Years War in which King John II of France was taken hostage?",
        "answer": "Battle of Poitiers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Discontent over the French loss at Poitiers and high taxes led to this peasant uprising. The leader of this rebellion, Guillaume Cale, was beheaded by Charles the Bad before the Battle of Mello.",
        "answer": "Jacquerie"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2009, Herman Van Rompuy was made the first permanent head of a council directing this organization. This organization was established by the Maastricht Treaty which absorbed groups led by the “Inner Six” and “Outer Seven.” In 2009, this organization passed the Treaty of Lisbon, which introduced Article 50 to its central document. The United Kingdom has attempted to leave, for ten points, what pan-national organization that includes countries like France and Germany?",
        "answer": [
          "European Union",
          "EU"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The European Union grew out of a commercial community overseeing the production of coal and this alloy of carbon and iron.",
        "answer": "steel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this modern-day state, British forces fought the Battle of Bloody Marsh as part of the War of Jenkins” Ear. The laws of Tribal Sovereignty were established in a court case stemming from Samuel Worcester’s [WOOST-er’s] arrest in this state. George III chartered this colony to both provide a haven for debtors as well as to provide a buffer between the British colonies and Spanish-controlled Florida. For ten points, name this state founded by James Oglethorpe from Savannah.",
        "answer": "Georgia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The decision in Worcester v. Georgia was handed down by this longest-serving Chief Justice who had earlier established judicial review in Marbury v. Madison.",
        "answer": "John Marshall"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the coronation of this man, several people were trampled to death as a crowd rushed to Khodynka field. On the advice of Sergei Witte, this man curbed his own power in the October Manifesto to appease the people. This man and his immediate family were executed in Yekaterinburg to prevent them from being rescued by the White Army. The 1917 October Revolution caused the resignation of, for ten points, what final Romanov ruler, the last Tsar of Russia?",
        "answer": "Nicholas II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nicholas II’s wife was obsessed with this Russian mystic who claimed he could heal their son of his hemophilia.",
        "answer": "Grigori Rasputin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man ordered the execution of Cuauht´emoc while en route to remove his rival Crist´obal de Olid at Triunfo de la Cruz. After being told to return from his expedition by the governor of Cuba, this man burned his own ships. La Malinche served as a translator for this man, who commanded European and Tlaxcala forces at the Battle of Otumba. Tenochtitlan was burned by, for ten points, what Spanish conquistador who destroyed the Aztec Empire?",
        "answer": "Hernan Cortes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During his conquest, Hernan Cortes overthrew this last Aztec Emperor.",
        "answer": [
          "Moctezuma II",
          "Montezuma II"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A massacre of these people was uncovered in the Sidr´on Cave system in Spain, indicating that cannibals ate the 15 dead. These people were fully wiped out during a very cold period of European history 40,000 years ago. This species, named for a valley in Germany, share 1 to 2 percent of its DNA with Homo sapiens. Prominent brows are a notable feature of, for ten points, what cave-dwelling hominid species?",
        "answer": "Neanderthals or Homo neanderthalis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Neanderthals are named for the Neander Valley, which is formed by a tributary of this major west German river. Nazi Germany violated the Treaty of Versailles in March 1936 by re-militarizing the land around this river.",
        "answer": [
          "Rhine",
          "Rhine River",
          "Rhineland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The 4th book of the Continuations of the Chronicle of Fredegar gives a biased account of this battle. This battle occurred after Odo the Great suffered multiple defeats at Narbonne and Bordeaux, leading his army to combine with Frankish forces. One side at this battle had no cavalry, opting to form the phalanx formation to combat Abd al-Rahman al-Ghafiqi’s horses. For ten points, name this victory by Charles Martel that turned back the Muslim invasion of Europe.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Tours",
          "Battle of Poitier"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Odo the Great, who had earlier fought the Umayyads at the Battle of Toulouse, was duke of this French region",
        "answer": "Aquitaine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A portrait of this man by Ingres [ahng] shows him seated on a throne while wearing a golden laurel. Jacques-Louis David [dah-VEED] painted numerous portraits of this man, including one at his study in the Tuileries [twee-luh-ree] Palace and another in which this man rides a rearing gray horse while crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this French Emperor who was painted leading troops at the Battle of Waterloo.",
        "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte or Napoleon I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The bottom left corner of David’s Napoleon Crossing the Alps includes the names of three famous generals inscribed on rocks. One is Bonaparte; name either of the other men.",
        "answer": [
          "Hannibal Barca and/or Charlemagne",
          "Carolus Magnus"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Wallingford guaranteed this king’s ascension to the throne and ended a conflict involving his mother, Empress Matilda. Following this man’s death, his son joined with Frederick Barbarossa and Philip Augustus on the Third Crusade. This king allegedly asked, “will no one rid me of this meddlesome priest,” prompting four knights to carry out an assassination in Canterbury Cathedral in 1170. For ten points, name this king of England who fathered Richard the Lionheart and John.",
        "answer": "Henry II of England"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "By despairing about the “meddlesome priest,” Henry II essentially ordered the murder of this Archbishop of Canterbury in 1170.",
        "answer": "Thomas a Becket"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With Zionist Theodor Herzl, this man came up with the Uganga Scheme to temporarily make a Jewish homeland in Africa. This man gave the Mansion House speech denouncing Germany’s actions during the Agadir Crisis. With Woodrow Wilson, Vittorio Orlando, and George Clemenceau, this man made up the “Big Four” at the Versailles Peace Talks. For ten points, name this Welshman that served as the British PM during the second half of World War I.",
        "answer": "David Lloyd George"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lloyd George served as Chancellor of the Exchequer under this Liberal UK Prime Minister who declared war on Germany after it violated Belgium’s neutrality.",
        "answer": "H.H. Asquith"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 1958 film about this battle starring John Mills and Richard Attenborough was partly based on the novel The Big Pick-Up. Another film about this battle was shot using very little CGI and twenty “Little Ships” which actually participated in this battle. That film about this battle, which was split into three sections named “The Sea,” “The Air,” and “The Mole,” starred Harry Styles and is widely considered to F be the best work of its director Christopher Nolan. For ten points, name this battle during which British and French forces were evacuated from France.",
        "answer": "Battle of Dunkirk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Dunkirk occurred in this year, the same year as the Battle for the Hague, the Battle of Zeeland, and the beginning of the Battle of Britain.",
        "answer": "1940 A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man issued numerous telegraphs to “cousin Willy” to avoid war during the July Crisis. Sergei Witte advised this man to enact legal reforms in order to stay in power, even though this man’s popularity had plummeted when his soldiers fired on father Georgy Gapon’s protesters on Bloody Sunday. This man issued the October Manifesto in an attempt to pacify disgruntled workers but was soon overthrown in the October Revolution by Lenin’s communists. For ten points, name the final tsar of Russia.",
        "answer": "Nicholas II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Nicholas II’s promised reforms in the October Manifesto was the establishment of this lawmaking body, which has since evolved into the lower house of Russia’s legislative assembly.",
        "answer": "Duma"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The world’s tallest statue of a woman commemorates this battle and is known as “The Motherland Calls.” Soldiers stationed at Kalach-on-the-Don were encircled as part of this battle’s Operation Uranus. A speech by Adolf Hitler named after this battle ends with him exclaiming “I do not want a second Verdun there!” An attempt to provide supplies to one side during Operation Winter Storm was thwarted by terrible weather at this 1942-43 battle. Over 1.7 million casualties occurred at, for ten points, what massive World War Two battle, where Germany surrendered to the Soviet Union? R",
        "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The initial German goal at the Battle of Stalingrad was to block this river on which Stalingrad lay, the longest river in Europe.",
        "answer": "Volga"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the Boer War, this man served as a journalist and escaped from prison after being captured by Boer troops. In one speech, this man urged his countrymen to fight on the beaches and landing areas and never give up. This man claimed that he had nothing to offer but “blood, toil, sweat, and tears.” After the resignation of Neville Chamberlain, this man rose to his highest position of Prime Minister and F led the U.K.’s staunch resistance to Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this influential British leader.",
        "answer": "Winston Churchill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Churchill’s resolve remained unshaken despite facing this Nazi bombing campaign from September 1940 to May 1941. Its name is taken from the German word for “Lightning.”",
        "answer": "The Blitz A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group attempted to work with U.S. forces in constructing a tunnel under Berlin during Operation Gold. This organization was embarrassed when Lionel Crabb disappeared while reconnoitering Portsmouth Dockyard. During the Cold War, this organization was infiltrated when Guy Burgess allowed the Soviet spy Kim Philby to join its ranks. This organization handled the ULTRA code during World War Two under the leadership of Stewart Menzies. For ten points, name this British agency that focuses on foreign intelligence, in contrast to its counterpart in Section 5.",
        "answer": [
          "MI6",
          "Secret Intelligence Service",
          "SIS"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Author Ian Fleming spent World War Two serving under the Director of Naval Intelligence, and his best known character is this MI6 agent whom Fleming based on actual agents he had met during the war.",
        "answer": "James Bond Page 4 of 10"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was recognized in the Treaty of Le Goulet, though he later lost the battle of Bouvines to its other signatory, Philip Augustus. This man refused to recognize Stephen Langton as Archbishop of Canterbury,leadingInnocentIIItoexcommunicatethismanin1209.AfterhewascorneredatRunnymede by disgruntled nobles, this man was forced to sign a document that outlined principles such as “habeas corpus.” For ten points, name this English king who signed the Magna Carta in 1215. R",
        "answer": [
          "John",
          "John Lackland"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John succeeded this brother, with a notably valiant nickname, as king after he was killed suppressing a revolt in France.",
        "answer": [
          "Richard I",
          "Richard the Lionhearted",
          "Richard Coeur de Lion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A king of this name became the final monarch to dismiss an English prime minister when he removed Lord Melbourne. Child labour was banned during the reign of a king of this name, the last of the Hanoverian dynasty. A king of this name took power when his predecessor’s Declaration of Indulgence led to that man’s overthrow. Rotten boroughs were eliminated in an attempt to expand votership when the “Great Reform Bill” was passed under a king of this name. For ten points, the Catholic James II was overthrown by a king of what name during the Glorious Revolution? R",
        "answer": "William"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "If Prince William, the grandson of Elizabeth II and current Duke of Cambridge, succeeds to the British throne, what will be his regnal number as King William?",
        "answer": "Five or Fifth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One company in this industry, prior to merging with Mo¨et et Chandon and Hennesy, had made products named Speedy and Noe. The founder of another company in this industry worked with Arthur D “Boy” Capel and created a “uniform for afternoon and evening” known as that founder’s namesake suit. That company made a famous number 5 product and was influenced by the “New Look” of Christian Dior. “The Little Black Dress” style comes from, for ten points, what industry whose companies include Louis Vuitton and Chanel?",
        "answer": "Fashion Industry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Louis Vuitton himself was the personal trunk maker and packer for Eugenie de Montijo, the wife of Napoleon III, and, as such, the last woman to hold this title.",
        "answer": "Empress of France T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A famous one of these places is named for a French aviation pioneer and fighter pilot, Roland Garros. Another of these places was known as the Jeu de Paume at the time it served as the venue for the 1789 meeting place of members of the Third Estate. One of these in Flushing Meadows is named after Arthur Ashe, while another in England saw champions like Andre Agassi and Bjorn Borg win titles on grass F surfaces. For ten points, name these sporting venues, one of which saw a namesake “oath” taken during the French Revolution.",
        "answer": "Tennis courts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This advocate for gender equality and social justice won 39 Grand Slam titles in her career, was a Time Person of the Year in 1975, and won the “Battle of the Sexes” against Bobby Riggs.",
        "answer": "Billie Jean King A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One section of this work contrasts one idea with the notion that “vexation may be succeeded by content [cun-TENT].” In this text’s first section, the author calls the title discipline “a road either to safety or to ruin.” One section of this text lists five effective uses of fire including burning baggage trains and as a means of tipping arrows to rain down on an enemy. Written during the reign of Shenzong this text was penned during the Spring and Autumn Period. For ten points, name this Chinese military D treatise written by Sun Tzu.",
        "answer": [
          "The Art of War",
          "Sunzi Bingfa"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the earliest notable English translations of The Art of War was by British museum curator Lionel Giles who also made a noted translation of the Analects, a collection of sayings attributed to this Chinese philosopher.",
        "answer": [
          "Confucius",
          "Kong Fuzi",
          "Master Kong T"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man ensured peace with Russia in the Reinsurance Treaty. This leader was depicted in the cartoon “Dropping the Pilot” after he was succeeded in one post. This man, who attempted to subvert the Catholic church with his policy of Kulturkampf, edited the Ems dispatch to begin a war with France. This practitioner of “realpolitik” noted that “the great questions of the time” would be resolved by “iron F and blood.” For ten points, name this “Iron Chancellor” who unified the German states in 1871.",
        "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bismarck was born in this independent German kingdom that led the drive to unification, was the leading state of the Empire of Germany, and was dissolved into the Weimar Republic in 1918.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Prussia A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This journalist wrote for the newspaper Avanti!, but during World War One abandoned both it and his country's Socialist Party. This prime minister's followers, sometimes dubbed \"Squadristis,\" were known as the Black Shirts. Declaring himself \"Il Duce,\" [[eel-DOO-cheh]] this man aligned with Nazi Germany, though his armed forces failed to secure North Africa or stop the Allied invasion of Sicily. For ten points, name this leader of Italy during most of World War Two.",
        "answer": "Benito Mussolini or Benito Amilcare Andrea Mussolini"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mussolini signed the Lateran Treaty to give independence to this tiny European city-state.",
        "answer": [
          "Vatican City State or Stato della Città del Vaticano",
          "or Status Civitatis Vaticanae"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man made a 300-mile long journey to Delagoa Bay following hisescapefroma Boer prison camp. The disaster of the Dardanelles campaign, especially the Battle of Gallipoli [[gah-LIH-poh-lee]], led to this man's resignation as First Lord of the Admiralty. Following the Dunkirk evacuation, this PM gave the \"This was their finest hour\" speech to the House of Commons. For ten points, name this prime minister of the UK during the majority of World War Two.",
        "answer": "WinstonChurchillor Sir Winston LeonardSpencerChurchill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Churchill served as War Secretary to this prime minister of Welsh descent who made up the Big Three at Versailles with Georges Clemenceau [[kleh-mahn-SOH]] and Woodrow Wilson.",
        "answer": "DavidLloyd George"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One king of these people named Cetshwayo [[ketsh-\"WHY\"-oh]] had his cause taken up by Lady Florence Dixie after spending two years in exile. Following a victory for these people at Isandlwana [[ee-sahn-JWAH-nah]], a contingent of their soldiers were cornered and defeated at Rorke's Drift. The \"horn of the buffalo\" formation was used by a regiment of these people known as the Impi. The conquests of Shaka led to the establishment of an empire of, for ten points, what people in Southern Africa?",
        "answer": "Zulu or amaZulu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the Battle of Blood River, 500 of these Dutch-descended travelers defeated 15,000 Zulu warriors. They fought a namesake war with the British at the turn of the 20th century.",
        "answer": [
          "Boers",
          "Afrikaners",
          "Voortrekkers",
          "Boer War"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "CHARLEMAGNE",
      "prompt": "Medieval emperor Charlemagne...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was crowned on Christmas 800 by Leo III, a holder of what top office of the Catholic\nChurch?",
          "answer": "Pope, the Papacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Instigated the \"Carolingian\" example of what sort of period in which arts and learning revive?",
          "answer": "renaissance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Launched a crusade against what Germanic people, who earlier joined with the Angles to\nconquer England?",
          "answer": "Saxons"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 797, took control of what currently second largest city in Spain?",
          "answer": "Barcelona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the son of what small-statured king?",
          "answer": "Pepin the Short, Pepin III, Pepin le Bref, Pippin der Kurze"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was gifted what kind of large animal, known as Abul-Abbas, by the Abbasid caliph?",
          "answer": "elephant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of which Germanic tribe who were earlier led by the Merovingians?",
          "answer": "Franks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the grandson of what Mayor of the Palace who won the Battle of Tours?",
          "answer": "Charles Martel, Carolus Martellus, Karl Martell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE SPANISH ARMADA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sent off in what historic year?",
          "answer": "1588"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempting to return England to what religion?",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Catholicism",
            "Catholic",
            "Catholicism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent against what Queen of England?",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Funded in part by Spanish conquests over what Native Americans of the Andes Mountains?",
          "answer": [
            "Incans",
            "Incas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Initially combatted by what commander of the Golden Hind?",
          "answer": [
            "Francis Drake",
            "Drake"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Shattered near the Munster and Connacht (pr. cuh-NOKT) areas of what island when it was\nblown off course on its return?",
          "answer": "Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organized by what Spanish king?",
          "answer": "Philip II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unsuccessfully commanded by what Spanish military officer?",
          "answer": [
            "Duke of Medina Sidonia",
            "Medina Sidonia",
            "Don Alonso Perez de Guzman y de Zuniga-Sotomayor",
            "Guzman"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "The Spanish Armada was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "EMANCIPATION OF SERFS",
      "prompt": "The emancipation of the world's largest serf population...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Occurred in what empire, which was ultimately ended by the deposition of Tsar Nicholas II?",
          "answer": [
            "Russian Empire",
            "Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Began in what year, also the year Abraham Lincoln's Presidency and the Civil War started?",
          "answer": "1861"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was instigated by what tsar, who was assassinated twenty years later?",
          "answer": "Alexander II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended the landlord veto over serfs engaging in what practice, the subject of the American\ncourt case Loving v. Virginia?",
          "answer": [
            "marriage",
            "weddings"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was part of the fallout from Russia's defeat by Britain, France, and Turkey in what war?",
          "answer": [
            "Crimean War",
            "Crimean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led radicals to support what political position that characterized the Nechaevists, Land and\nLiberty, and The People's Will?",
          "answer": [
            "anarchism",
            "nihilism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Set up what system of elected provincial councils?",
          "answer": [
            "zemstvos"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Required that former serfs do what for forty-nine years?",
          "answer": [
            "submit redemption payments to former owners",
            "redemption payment"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "WORLD WAR I",
      "prompt": "In World War I, who or what was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The country which exited the war following the Bolshevik Revolution and organized the\nUSSR five years later?",
          "answer": [
            "Russia",
            "Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic",
            "Soviet Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The palace outside Paris where the main peace treaty was signed?",
          "answer": "Versailles"
        },
        {
          "question": "The archduke whose assassination sparked the conflict?",
          "answer": [
            "Franz Ferdinand",
            "Francis Ferdinand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The assassin responsible for that archduke's death?",
          "answer": [
            "Gavrilo Princip",
            "Princip"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The country whose violated neutrality was a proximate cause of Britain’s entering the war?",
          "answer": "Belgium"
        },
        {
          "question": "The high commander of American forces in the war?",
          "answer": [
            "John Pershing",
            "John Joseph Pershing",
            "Pershing",
            "Black Jack Pershing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The German war plan which involved quickly defeating France before fighting Russia?",
          "answer": [
            "Schlieffen Plan",
            "Schlieffen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The August 1914 battle where Hindenburg and Ludendorff destroyed a Russian army?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Tannenberg",
            "Tannenberg"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE SOUTH SEA BUBBLE",
      "prompt": "England's South Sea Bubble scandal of 1720...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Arose over a company which transported what kind of people in the \"Middle Passage\" after\nforcible abduction from Africa?",
          "answer": [
            "slaves"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to the creation of what office, later held by Margaret Thatcher and David Cameron?",
          "answer": [
            "Prime Minister of the United Kingdom",
            "Prime Minister",
            "First Lord of the Treasury"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Occurred during the reign of what first Hanoverian king?",
          "answer": "George I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to the ascension of what party, which opposed the Tories in the eighteenth-century British\nparty system?",
          "answer": [
            "Whigs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Temporarily soured the English investor class on what form of business entity which preceded\ncorporations and was prominent during the Age of Exploration?",
          "answer": "joint-stock company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arose from an attempt to exploit the Treaty of Utrecht, which ended what war in 1713?",
          "answer": [
            "War of the Spanish Succession",
            "Spanish Succession"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was resolved by what politician who dominated the British government until 1742?",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Walpole",
            "Walpole"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Caused the creation of what institution, which manages UK monetary policy?",
          "answer": "Bank of England"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "POST-WAR ITALY",
      "prompt": "In Italy after World War II, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ideology advocated by the Red Brigades terrorist group and Italy's neighbor Yugoslavia?",
          "answer": [
            "Communism",
            "Marxism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organized crime phenomenon which was curtailed in the \"Maxi trial?\"",
          "answer": "the mafia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization formed by the Maastricht Treaty which Italy was an architect of?",
          "answer": [
            "European Union",
            "EU"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Western military alliance which orchestrated Operation Gladio in Italy?",
          "answer": [
            "NATO",
            "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Media mogul who became Italy's right-wing prime minister three times and was frequently\ncharged with corruption?",
          "answer": [
            "Silvio Berlusconi",
            "Berlusconi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Milan-based designer who founded what is now Italy's largest men's fashion house in 1975?",
          "answer": [
            "Giorgio Armani",
            "Armani"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Umbrella auto manufacturer which now owns Ferrari, Maserati, and Chrysler?",
          "answer": "Fiat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name commonly given to the period of political violence from 1969 to the mid-1980s?",
          "answer": [
            "Years of Lead",
            "Anni di piombo"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AVIATION",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the last name of Orville and Wilbur, the builders of the first successful airplane?",
          "answer": [
            "Wright",
            "Wright Brothers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first woman to fly solo non-stop across the Atlantic in 1932, but disappeared in the Pacific\nfive years later?",
          "answer": [
            "Amelia Earhart",
            "Earhart"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the nickname of German WWI ace Manfred von Richthofen?",
          "answer": "The Red Baron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first pilot to break the sound barrier?",
          "answer": [
            "Chuck Yeager",
            "Yeager"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the type of aircraft invented by the Montgolfier [mohn-GOAL-fee-ay] brothers in 1783?",
          "answer": "hot air balloon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the airplane that Charles Lindbergh flew for the first solo non-stop trans-Atlantic flight?",
          "answer": "The Spirit of St. Louis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Russian designer of the R-4 helicopter?",
          "answer": [
            "Igor Sikorsky",
            "Sikorsky"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the nickname of the H-4 Hercules, a flying boat designed by Howard Hughes?",
          "answer": "Spruce Goose"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In the history of human flight, who or what..."
    },
    {
      "category": "EUROPEAN NAVIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The country whose Baltic Sea ports include Kaliningrad and St. Petersburg?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The term for German submarines that harassed Allied shipping during World Wars 1 and 2?",
          "answer": [
            "U-boats",
            "Unterseeboots",
            "U boats"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The fleet of over 100 ships whose invasion of England was thwarted by Francis Drake?",
          "answer": "Spanish Armada"
        },
        {
          "question": "The country that has naval yards at Szczecin [st-etch-in] and Gdansk?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "The battle at which Lord Nelson died?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Trafalgar",
            "Trafalgar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The French city where British fishing boats and little ships ferried evacuated Allied soldiers from the\nNazis?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Dunkirk",
            "Dunkirk"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The October 1571 galley battle in which the Holy League devastated an Ottoman fleet in the Ionian\nSea?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Lepanto",
            "Lepanto"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Nazi operation that would have invaded Britain if naval superiority had been achieved?",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Sealion",
            "Sealion"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In European naval history, what is..."
    },
    {
      "category": "MODERN BRITISH PMS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the current PM (2025)?",
          "answer": "Keir Starmer"
        },
        {
          "question": "served during most of World War II, offering nothing but “blood, toil, tears, and sweat?”",
          "answer": [
            "Winston Churchill",
            "Churchill"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was known as the Iron Lady?",
          "answer": [
            "Margaret Thatcher",
            "Thatcher"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "attended the 1919 Paris Peace Conference and helped organize the Treaty of Versailles?",
          "answer": [
            "David Lloyd George",
            "Lloyd George"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "signed the Munich Agreement with Hitler, proclaiming “peace in our time”?",
          "answer": [
            "Neville Chamberlain",
            "Chamberlain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "replaced his predecessor as the new Labour PM at the 1945 Potsdam Conference?",
          "answer": [
            "Clement Attlee",
            "Attlee"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was criticized for sending troops to Iraq in 2003?",
          "answer": [
            "Tony Blair",
            "Blair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was comparably less criticized for sending troops to Iraq in 1991?",
          "answer": [
            "John Major",
            "Major"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which British Prime Minister from the 20th and 21st centuries..."
    },
    {
      "category": "ENGLISH CITIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is its capital, led by Mayor Boris Johnson?",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to the oldest English-speaking university, a rival of Cambridge?",
          "answer": "Oxford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the Merseyside port where the Beatles formed?",
          "answer": "Liverpool"
        },
        {
          "question": "Has a shrine to Archbishop Thomas Becket to which pilgrims traveled in a work by Chaucer?",
          "answer": "Canterbury"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the setting of the Robin Hood legend, as its sheriff tried to capture Robin Hood?",
          "answer": "Nottingham"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the launching city for the Titanic and for the Pilgrim-carrying Mayflower?",
          "answer": "Southampton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost its six-hundred-year old cathedral to a German air raid in November 1940?",
          "answer": "Coventry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the setting for The Condition of the Working Class in England by Engels?",
          "answer": "Manchester"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which English city..."
    },
    {
      "category": "COUNTRIES IN WORLD WAR II",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was allied with Germany until the Allies invaded it and captured Rome?",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first to be invaded by Germany, on September 1, 1939?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created the Maginot Line to defend against Germany, but quickly surrendered anyway?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was invaded by Nazi Germany during Operation Barbarossa and later captured Berlin?",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "USSR",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "CCCP",
            "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Allied with Germany after it lost the Winter War?",
          "answer": "Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a German invasion at Trondheim, and was led by Vidkun Quisling?",
          "answer": "Norway"
        },
        {
          "question": "Maintained a policy of neutrality while buying stolen German gold?",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Eastern European site of the Ploiesti [ploy-esh-tee] oilfields, vital to the Nazi war effort?",
          "answer": "Romania"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In World War II, which country..."
    },
    {
      "category": "EUROPEAN LEFTIST POLITICS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Former largest socialist country in Europe, which collapsed into Russia and other countries in 1991.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "USSR",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "CCCP",
            "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorfully named political movement that, in numerous countries, is a left-leaning political party that\nseeks environmental reform and peace?",
          "answer": [
            "Green parties",
            "Green"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Faction of communists in Russia that split from the Mensheviks in 1903.",
          "answer": "Bolsheviks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Britain’s New Labour movement who served as Prime Minister from 1997-2007.",
          "answer": [
            "Tony Blair",
            "Blair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alliance of socialist countries in eastern Europe that was formed to oppose NATO.",
          "answer": [
            "Warsaw Pact",
            "Warsaw"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Radical government that took over Paris when under threat during the Franco-Prussian War.",
          "answer": [
            "Paris Commune",
            "Commune"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the style of social and economic policies in Scandinavia that combine capitalism with a\nstrong welfare state.",
          "answer": [
            "Nordic model",
            "Nordic",
            "Nordic economics",
            "Nordic democracy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First UK Labour Prime Minister, who was negatively affected by the forged Zinoviev letter.",
          "answer": [
            "Ramsay MacDonald",
            "Ramsay"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "QUEENS OF EUROPE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Longest reigning monarch of the United Kingdom.",
          "answer": [
            "Elizabeth II",
            "Queen Elizabeth II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Iberian country ruled by just two queens named Maria, who also ruled over Brazil.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pious queen of Castile who authorized the first Spanish colonization efforts and was married to\nFerdinand of Aragon.",
          "answer": [
            "Isabella",
            "Isabella I of Castile",
            "Isabella I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Beheaded queen who legendarily said “Let them eat cake!”",
          "answer": "Marie Antoniette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Stuart queen who tried to overthrow Elizabeth I and was subsequently executed.",
          "answer": [
            "Mary Queen of Scots",
            "Mary I of Scotland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Low country in Northern Europe ruled by Queen Beatrix in the 20th century.",
          "answer": [
            "the Netherlands",
            "Holland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Position held by two of Henry VIII’s queens, who governed in place of a monarch who cannot rule\ndue to absence, sickness, or youth.",
          "answer": [
            "Queen regent",
            "regent"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Duchess of Aquitaine who became Queen of both England and France and helped form the Angevin\nEmpire.",
          "answer": [
            "Eleanor of Aquitaine",
            "Eleanor"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "SCRAMBLE FOR AFRICA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Type of project that Britain planned to build, allowing trains to travel from the Cape to Cairo.",
          "answer": [
            "railroad",
            "rail",
            "railway"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that colonized much of West Africa after the exploration of Pierre Savorgnan.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that pushed for additional territories through the weltpolitik of Kaiser Wilhelm II.",
          "answer": "Germany"
        },
        {
          "question": "British colony in West Africa that grouped together the Hausa, Igbo, and Yoruba people.",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "European country that introduced the Pink Map to connect its colonies of Angola and Mozambique.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region that was carved up by the British, French, and Italians in the Horn of Africa.",
          "answer": [
            "Somaliland",
            "Somali",
            "Somalia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "West African country, once a British colony known as the Gold Coast, where the Ashanti fought\nseveral wars.",
          "answer": "Ghana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern day country that was the site of German South-West Africa and a genocide of the Herero\npeople.",
          "answer": "Namibia"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "CHARLES V, HOLY ROMAN EMPEROR",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Iberian kingdom where he ruled as “Charles I,” to the south of France.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Spain",
            "Spain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty that ruled the Holy Roman Empire for three centuries and included Charles V.",
          "answer": [
            "Habsburg Dynasty",
            "Habsburg",
            "House of Habsburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious movement that expressed discontent with the Catholic Church and began during his reign.",
          "answer": [
            "Protestant Reformation",
            "Reformation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Landmark exploration project he supported by funding Ferdinand Magellan’s 1519 voyage.",
          "answer": [
            "circumnavigation of the world",
            "circumnavigation",
            "sailing around the world"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Action he took to voluntarily leave his various thrones, a few years before his death.",
          "answer": "abdication"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of religious institution where he lived for two years after leaving the throne.",
          "answer": "monastery"
        },
        {
          "question": "French king that fought Charles in the Italian Wars but was captured at Pavia.",
          "answer": "Francis I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Imperial city where, in 1555, Charles V and the Schmalkaldic League agreed to the principle of “cuius\nregio, eius religio.”",
          "answer": [
            "Peace of Augsburg",
            "Aubsburg"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "THE INDUSTRIAL REVOLUTION",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European nation with capital London where the Industrial Revolution began.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Industry where revolution led to increased crop output and a growing population.",
          "answer": [
            "agriculture",
            "farming",
            "farm"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Invention that powered many plants when moving water was unavaliable, invented by James Watt.",
          "answer": "steam engine"
        },
        {
          "question": "The crop sourced from Egypt, India, and the American South, which fueled textile mills.",
          "answer": "cotton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Metal that was tempered into steel and used to build stronger buildings.",
          "answer": "iron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Industrial process used to create steel from otherwise unhelpful smelting byproducts by blowing air\nto remove impurities.",
          "answer": [
            "Bessemer process",
            "Bessemer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The multi-spindle frame, invented in the 1760s, that allowed for the mass production of yarn.",
          "answer": "spinning jenny"
        },
        {
          "question": "Engineer who designed the Great Western Railway, as well as pre-fabricated hospitals for the Crimean\nWar effort.",
          "answer": [
            "Isambard Kingdom Brunel",
            "Brunel"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "PLAYERS IN THE SUEZ CRISIS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who responded with a namesake doctrine offering aid to threatened Middle Eastern\ncountries.",
          "answer": [
            "Dwight Eisenhower",
            "Eisenhower"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet Premier who threatened missile attacks and, two weeks later, ranted “We will bury you!”",
          "answer": [
            "Nikita Khrushchev",
            "Khrushchev"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian President who was to be ousted by the invasion.",
          "answer": [
            "Gamal Abdel Nasser",
            "Nasser"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British Prime Minister who resigned in its wake.",
          "answer": [
            "Sir Anthony Eden",
            "Eden"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former British Prime Minister who questioned the early end to hostilities.",
          "answer": [
            "Winston Churchill",
            "Churchill"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Canadian Prime Minister who won a Nobel Peace Prize for ending the Crisis.",
          "answer": [
            "Lester Pearson",
            "Pearson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-Aligned leader who maintained India’s neutrality in the Crisis and helped broker peace.",
          "answer": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Nehru"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "then-UN Secretary-General who also assisted in ceasefire talks.",
          "answer": [
            "Dag Hammarskjold",
            "Hammarskjold"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Regarding the 1956 Suez Crisis, who was the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "FRENCH ROYALTY",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Religious group persecuted by Louis the Ninth for charging interest on loans, an example of\nanti-Semitism.",
          "answer": [
            "Jewish people",
            "Jews"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountainous country east of France from which Louis the Twelfth hired many mercenaries.",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Shared name of cathedrals in Rheims, where many French kings were crowned, and Paris, which\ntranslates as “Our Lady.”",
          "answer": "Notre Dame"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lowest class of feudal society, whose peasant members were allowed by Louis the Tenth to buy their\nfreedom.",
          "answer": "serfs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Husband of Marie Antoinette.",
          "answer": [
            "Louis XVI",
            "Louis 16"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Duchy, once led by William the Conqueror, that Louis the Sixth tried to recover from England.",
          "answer": "Normandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom that failed to renew its Auld Alliance with France during the reign of Louis the Eleventh.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Scotland",
            "Scotland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty that rose to power after the death of Louis the Fifth, from which all subsequent French kings\nwere descended.",
          "answer": [
            "House of Capet",
            "Capet"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "THE FRENCH AND INDIAN WAR",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American major who led Virginian forces during the war and later served as Commander-in-Chief of\nthe Continental Army.",
          "answer": [
            "George Washington",
            "Washington"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "River between the US and modern Canada that was targeted by the British as the center of French\nsettlement.",
          "answer": "St. Lawrence River"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that marked the western boundary of land that France ceded to Britain.",
          "answer": "Mississippi River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that ended the war; the name of the city is enough.",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of Paris 1763",
            "Paris",
            "Treaty of Paris"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city of New France that was captured by the British after the Battle of the Plains of Abraham.",
          "answer": [
            "Quebec City",
            "Quebec"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Native American confederation, a union of five tribes, that sided with the British during the war.",
          "answer": [
            "Iroquois Confederacy",
            "Iroquois"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British edict that forbade post-war American settlement west of the Appalachians.",
          "answer": "Proclamation of 1763"
        },
        {
          "question": "British general who died while commanding a disastrous expedition to take Fort Duquesne [do-kayne].",
          "answer": [
            "Edward Braddock",
            "Braddock",
            "Braddock Expedition",
            "Braddock Campaign"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "Royal Houses of Europe",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tudor queen of England who ruled from 1558 to 1603.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian royal house whose hereditary rule was passed to Maria Theresa via the Pragmatic Sanction.",
          "answer": "House of Habsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last French royal house before the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "House of Bourbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "French royal house founded by Hugh after the end of the Carolingians.",
          "answer": "House of Capet"
        },
        {
          "question": "German house that ruled a namesake state and Britain after the reign of George I.",
          "answer": "House of Hanover"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese royal house that ruled until Portugal was inherited by Spain. It was eventually succeeded by the House of Braganza.",
          "answer": "House of Aviz"
        },
        {
          "question": "House that ruled a unified Italy after its namesake state united the peninsula under the prime minister Cavour.",
          "answer": "House of Savoy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Frankish house that ruled the Holy Roman Empire under Conrad II. It also names a set of Frankish law that only allowed for male succession.",
          "answer": "House of Salian or Salic Law"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "JEWS IN EUROPE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "3,000-year-old language, used to write most of the Tanakh, whose modern form has adopted numerous\nEuropean influences.",
          "answer": "Hebrew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighborhoods where minorities, like Jews in Nazi-controlled Warsaw, were forced to live.",
          "answer": "ghettoes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Occupation that Jews were often forced to take because they were not affected by the Catholic\nChurch’s ban on usury. Examples include the Rothschild family.",
          "answer": [
            "banker",
            "bank",
            "moneylender",
            "lender",
            "loans",
            "charging interest on loans"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for outbursts of violence against Jews in the Russian Empire.",
          "answer": "pogroms"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group that was often tolerant of Jews, since it classified them as dhimmi, or people of the\nbook.",
          "answer": [
            "Islam",
            "Muslims"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Decree issued by Ferdinand and Isabella that forced all Jews in Spain to either convert or flee into\nexile.",
          "answer": [
            "Alhambra Decree",
            "Alhambra"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "19th century “affair” in which a Jewish French army officer was falsely accused of treason.",
          "answer": [
            "Alfred Dreyfus affair",
            "Dreyfus",
            "Dreyfus affair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "12th century Jewish scholar born in Cordova who wrote a code of Jewish law called the Mishneh\nTorah.",
          "answer": [
            "Maimonides",
            "Moses ben Maimon",
            "ben Maimon"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "WORLD WAR I",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Soldier who was wounded at the Somme and blinded in a gas attack, then later led Nazi Germany.",
          "answer": [
            "Adolf Hitler",
            "Hitler"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Archduke of Austria-Hungary who was shot in Sarajevo in 1914.",
          "answer": [
            "Archduke Franz Ferdinand",
            "Franz Ferdinand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Sick Man of Europe” that joined the Central Powers in October 1914.",
          "answer": [
            "Ottoman Empire",
            "Ottoman"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation that sent David Lloyd George to the Paris Peace Conference.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "United Kingdom",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1914 battle where the German advance was halted along a namesake river, leading to trench warfare.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of the Marne River",
            "Marne",
            "Battle of the Marne"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1915 Allied campaign that failed to take Anzac Cove and never reached Constantinople.",
          "answer": [
            "Gallipoli Campaign",
            "Gallipoli",
            "Dardanelles Campaign",
            "Dardanelles",
            "Battle of Canakkale",
            "Canakkale"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed German plan to capture Paris in six weeks by sweeping through Belgium.",
          "answer": [
            "Schlieffen Plan",
            "Schlieffen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1914 battle that caused Alexander Samsonov, the losing general, to commit suicide.",
          "answer": [
            "Second Battle of Tannenberg",
            "Tannenberg",
            "Battle of Tannenberg"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "Antarctica",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Central Antarctic location where longitude is meaningless.",
          "answer": "Geographic South Pole"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protective layer of the atmosphere in which a hole is open over Antarctica.",
          "answer": "ozone layer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose sightseeing Flight 901 crashed into Mount Erebus in 1979, having taken off from Auckland.",
          "answer": "New Zealand"
        },
        {
          "question": "flight.",
          "answer": "Sir Edmund Hillary"
        },
        {
          "question": "British explorer who died in 1912 leading the Terra Nova expedition.",
          "answer": "Robert Falcon Scott"
        },
        {
          "question": "Norwegian explorer whose team beat the British Terra Nova party to their objective and survived the return journey.",
          "answer": "Roald Amundsen"
        },
        {
          "question": "British explorer whose failed mission on the Endurance, incredibly, resulted in no deaths.",
          "answer": "Sir Ernest Shackleton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian research station where the coldest temperature on Earth was recorded. Its name means “East.”",
          "answer": "Vostok Station"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century European Leaders",
      "prompt": "Given information about a leader, name the country in which...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister Aldo Moro was kidnapped, murdered, and abandoned in Rome.",
          "answer": "Italy or Italian Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian X [the tenth] rode through the streets of Copenhagen during Nazi occupation.",
          "answer": "Denmark"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clement Attlee and the Labour Party created the National Health Service.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurt Waldheim was elected President despite lying about his service in the Wehrmacht, which he joined after the Nazis annexed this country.",
          "answer": "Republic of Austria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Erich Honecker advocated “consumer socialism” and Walter Ulbricht’s “New Economic System” ruffled Communist feathers.",
          "answer": "East Germany or the German Democratic Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nicolae Ceausescu [cho-sess-koo] was overthrown in a 1989 revolution.",
          "answer": "Romania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rysto Ryti led the nation in the Continuation War against the Soviets.",
          "answer": "Republic of Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ante Paveli´c [an-tay pah-veh-lich] established the Ustashe regime within Yugoslavia.",
          "answer": "Independent State of Croatia if Yugoslavia is answered before mentioned, prompt and finish reading the part"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Opium Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that lost both Opium Wars to Britain.",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reigning British queen during the 19th century Opium Wars.",
          "answer": "Victoria"
        },
        {
          "question": "European nation that joined Britain during the Second Opium War after the execution of Auguste Chapdelaine [oh-GOOST shap-deh-LAN].",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty in power during the Opium Wars. It fell during the Xinhai [shin-hai] Revolution of 1911.",
          "answer": "Qing Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where the unequal treaty ending the First Opium War was signed.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Nanjing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city where Commissioner Lin destroyed the opium that started the First Opium War.",
          "answer": "Canton or Guangzhou"
        },
        {
          "question": "Waterway, first connected during the Sui Dynasty, that the British blocked during the Opium Wars.",
          "answer": "Grand Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Event that sparked the Second Opium War, when officials seized the namesake merchant ship.",
          "answer": "Arrow incident"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Scotland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tartan-patterned garments, similar to skirts, that originated in the Scottish Highlands.",
          "answer": "kilts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Musical instrument long considered a tool of war in the Scottish army, consisting of a chanter, drones, and a blowstick.",
          "answer": "bagpipes"
        },
        {
          "question": "London church where Edward Longshanks brought the captured Stone of Scone in 1296.",
          "answer": "Westminster Abbey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Knight who joined Andrew Moray to beat the English at Stirling Bridge, eight years before he was hanged for treason.",
          "answer": "William Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "1995 quasi-historical film in which Mel Gibson plays that knight.",
          "answer": "Braveheart"
        },
        {
          "question": "14th century King of Scots who beat Edward II at Bannnockburn in 1314.",
          "answer": "Robert the Bruce or Robert I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellions in 1715 and 1745 that sought to restore a Catholic monarch to the British throne.",
          "answer": "Jacobite rebellions or Jacobite risings, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Last pitched battle on British soil, a 1746 battle that ended the rebellions in the previous question.",
          "answer": "Battle of Culloden Moor"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "World War I",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Structures dug into the ground that defined much of the combat.",
          "answer": [
            "trenches",
            "trench warfare, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austro-Hungarian Archduke whose assassination by Serbian nationalists kicked off the war.",
          "answer": "Archduke Franz Ferdinand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Kaiser of the German Empire, who reigned during the war.",
          "answer": "Wilhelm II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Month in 1914 that names the crisis during which Austria gave Serbia an ultimatum.",
          "answer": [
            "July",
            "July Ultimatum",
            "July Crisis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ocean liner that was sunk by a German U-boat on May 7, 1915, killing nearly 1,200 people.",
          "answer": "RMS Lusitania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alliance of Britain, France, and Russia formed in 1907 that fought the Central Powers.",
          "answer": "Triple Entente"
        },
        {
          "question": "Peninsula that twice erupted into war, the first of which saw a namesake league fight the Ottoman Empire.",
          "answer": [
            "Balkan Peninsula",
            "the Balkans"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed German plan to force a French surrender by invading through Belgium.",
          "answer": "Schlieffen Plan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "European Leaders",
      "prompt": "Given the politician, name the country they govern.",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Chancellor Angela Merkel, a member of the Bundestag.",
          "answer": [
            "Federal Republic of Germany",
            "Bundesrepublik Deutschland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Theresa May, who replaced David Cameron after the Brexit vote.",
          "answer": "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emmanuel Macron, who defeated Marine le Pen in 2017.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Andrzej Duda, a former member of the Sejm [same].",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Petro Poroshenko, who ran for President after the Euromaidan protests.",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Giuseppe Conte, who became Prime Minister after lengthy negotiations between the Five Star Movement and Lega Nord.",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mark Rutte, who responded to the Malaysia Flight 17 attack as Prime Minister of the country from which the plane departed.",
          "answer": "The Netherlands"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alain Berset, a member of a Federal Council that was established in an 1848 Constitution.",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battles Around the World",
      "prompt": "Given the battle, name the modern-day country in which it took place.",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tamerlane’s 1398 sack of Delhi.",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dien Bien Phu, in what was then French Indochina.",
          "answer": "Vietnam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Zama, ending the Second Punic War.",
          "answer": "Tunisia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle of Borodino, which was depicted in War and Peace.",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battles of El Alamein during World War II.",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle of Adowa, or Adwa, a massive victory for Menelik II.",
          "answer": "Ethiopia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle of Red Cliffs, a massive loss for Cao Cao [sow sow].",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Raid on the Medway, led by Willem van Ghent.",
          "answer": [
            "England",
            "Great Britain",
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "European Economics",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Common currency adopted by much of the European Union in 2002.",
          "answer": "euro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Energy resource whose English mines were shut down in a 1980s strike that was busted by Margaret Thatcher.",
          "answer": "coal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Food resource that was the subject of Iceland/England territorial disputes, a so-called “War” in the North Atlantic.",
          "answer": [
            "fish",
            "Cod War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Bubbly wine that, by EU law, must come from a namesake region in northern France.",
          "answer": "Champagne"
        },
        {
          "question": "German regime that underwent immense inflation between the World Wars.",
          "answer": "Weimar Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "14th and 15th century league consisting of guilds and towns in northern Europe around the Baltic Sea.",
          "answer": [
            "Hanseatic League",
            "Hansa"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city-state of that league, a Free Imperial City in north Germany.",
          "answer": "Lubeck"
        },
        {
          "question": "Friedrich von Hayek magnum opus, a work that argued that socialism inevitably leads to economic and social oppression.",
          "answer": "The Road to Serfdom or Der Weg zur Knechtschaft"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Elizabeth I",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Religion whose persecution intensified in her later years as she embraced Protestantism.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Playwright patronized by Elizabeth who wrote Hamlet and Romeo and Juliet.",
          "answer": "William Shakespeare"
        },
        {
          "question": "London castle where Elizabeth was imprisoned during Wyatt’s Rebellion.",
          "answer": "Tower of London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Half-sister and predecessor of Elizabeth who got her nickname from violent persecution of Protestants.",
          "answer": [
            "Bloody Mary",
            "Mary I",
            "Mary Tudor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King who succeeded Elizabeth and established the House of Stuart in England.",
          "answer": [
            "James I",
            "James VI of Scotland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Privateer employed by Britain who “singed the beard of the King of Spain” in a raid at Cadiz.",
          "answer": "Sir Francis Drake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bill that established Elizabeth as the head of the Church of England, replacing a Bill of the same name from Henry VIII’s reign.",
          "answer": "Act of Supremacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spymaster and secretary to Elizabeth who secured the execution of Mary, Queen of Scots.",
          "answer": "Sir Francis Walsingham Foreign Intervention in Central and South America Name the..."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century European Politicians",
      "prompt": "Name the politician who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founded the Republic of Turkey after World War I and gave himself a name meaning “father of the Turks”.",
          "answer": [
            "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Became the first president of post-Soviet Russia after standing on a tank to deliver a speech during a coup attempt.",
          "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Established a Nazi puppet government in World War II-era Norway, where his name now means traitor.",
          "answer": "Vidkun Quisling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founded the Solidarity movement and became the first president of post-Communist Poland.",
          "answer": "Lech Walesa , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ordered the sinking of the Rainbow Warrior and was the first Socialist elected President of France.",
          "answer": "Franc¸ois Mitterrand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Issued a 1917 declaration calling for the establishment of a Jewish state on behalf of the British foreign office.",
          "answer": [
            "Arthur Balfour",
            "Balfour Declaration"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the Velvet Revolution in Czechoslovakia and was the first President of the Czech Republic.",
          "answer": "Vaclav Havel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served as Viceroy of India from 1899 to 1905 and names a boundary line between Poland and modern Belarus",
          "answer": [
            "George Curzon",
            "Curzon Line"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Poland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City that replaced Krakow in 1793 as the Polish capital and remains the capital today.",
          "answer": "Warsaw"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion adopted by Mieszko I in 966 after a lengthy process of converting pagan tribes.",
          "answer": [
            "Christianity",
            "Roman Catholicism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that, along with Austria and Russia, partitioned Poland in 1793.",
          "answer": "Prussia"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which Polish nationals like Casimir Pulaski fought and died in Savannah.",
          "answer": "American Revolutionary War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ottoman Sultan who declared war with Poland over Moldavia. An earlier sultan of the same name founded the Ottoman Empire.",
          "answer": "Osman I and/or II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty whose rule of Poland ended with Sigismund II’s successor Henry de Valois. It ruled Poland from 1386 to 1572.",
          "answer": "Jagiellonian Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "War fought by Poland against Ivan the Terrible over a region relinquished by Russia in the Peace of Jam Zapolski.",
          "answer": "Livonian War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Polish king during the Great Northern War who developed the city of Dresden and briefly abdicated the throne.",
          "answer": "Augustus the Strong or Augustus II"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Winston Churchill",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War in which he served as Prime Minister of the UK.",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country from which his troops evacuated from Dunkirk.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term he used in 1946 to describe Soviet domination of Eastern Europe “from Stettin...to Trieste.”",
          "answer": "Iron Curtain"
        },
        {
          "question": "German city in Saxony whose brutal firebombing he authorized.",
          "answer": "Dresden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed military campaign that led him to resign as Lord of the Admiralty in 1915.",
          "answer": [
            "Gallipoli Campaign",
            "Dardanelles Campaign"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King whose abdication crisis over Wallis Simpson nearly ended Churchill’s political career.",
          "answer": "Edward VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who succeeded him as Prime Minister in 1945.",
          "answer": "Clement Attlee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister under which he served as Chancellor of the Exchequer in the late 1920s.",
          "answer": "Stanley Baldwin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Early Democracy in Britain",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1215 document that formed the basis of British democracy.",
          "answer": [
            "Magna Carta Libertatum",
            "Great Charter of the Liberties"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Town outside Windsor where that document was signed.",
          "answer": "Runnymede"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legislative body, containing the House of Lords, that gained new powers after 1215.",
          "answer": "Parliament"
        },
        {
          "question": "English King who was forced to give up some of his power in 1215.",
          "answer": [
            "King John I",
            "John Lackland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Noble rank held by Robert Fitzwalter and the other men rebelling against that king’s rule.",
          "answer": "baron"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where a set of 1258 “Provisions” created more representation, and where the oldest English- speaking university is found.",
          "answer": "Provisions of Oxford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who annulled the 1215 document.",
          "answer": "Innocent III"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who, in exchange for a tax, reconfirmed that 1215 document.",
          "answer": [
            "Edward I of England",
            "Edward Longshanks"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Russian Federation",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Russian capital city that has expanded past its Third Ring Road.",
          "answer": "Moscow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Communist superpower, in which it was the largest member.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "USSR",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "CCCP",
            "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who served as Prime Minister for four years in between his first and current terms as President.",
          "answer": "Vladimir Putin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country from which it seized Sevastopol in 2014.",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who succeeded Mikhail Gorbachev as first President of post-1991 Russia.",
          "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who oversaw the Russo-Georgian War in 2008.",
          "answer": "Dmitry Medvedev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region containing Grozny that has fought Russia for independence.",
          "answer": "Chechnya"
        },
        {
          "question": "Month in which a coup against Gorbachev resulted in the creation of the Russian Federation.",
          "answer": "August Coup"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Anti-Semitism",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Water source Jews were often accused of poisoning.",
          "answer": "wells"
        },
        {
          "question": "Banking family started by Mayer Amschel whose massive wealth led to anti-Semitic conspiracies.",
          "answer": "Rothschild"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sectioned-off parts of cities where Jews were forced to live, as in Nazi-controlled Warsaw.",
          "answer": "ghetto"
        },
        {
          "question": "November 1938 event in which Jewish businesses were destroyed in one night in Nazi Germany.",
          "answer": [
            "Kristallnacht",
            "Night of Broken Glass"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for a campaign in which Jews or other minorities are massacred, particularly as in the Pale of Settlement.",
          "answer": "pogrom"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that established the Pale of Settlement.",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "French-Jewish army officer who was the center of a political affair in France after being wrongly arrested.",
          "answer": "Alfred Dreyfus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Myth that Jews were responsible for Germany’s defeat in World War I.",
          "answer": "stab-in-the-back myth"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Joan of Arc",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country she supported against England in the Hundred Years” War.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose siege she relieved, catapulting her to fame.",
          "answer": "Orleans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Method by which she was executed.",
          "answer": "burning at the stake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crime she was executed for which she committed by disguising herself.",
          "answer": "cross-dressing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Monarch who supported Joan and was crowned in Reims [RONCE] Cathedral in 1429.",
          "answer": "Charles VII"
        },
        {
          "question": "City, the stronghold for the English, where she was temporarily imprisoned.",
          "answer": "Rouen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Town in northern France where she was captured.",
          "answer": "Compiegne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Faction that captured her, supporters of John the Fearless.",
          "answer": [
            "Burgundians",
            "Burgundy"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of the Bulge",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that launched their final major offensive to begin the battle F",
          "answer": [
            "Nazi Germany",
            "Deutschland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Allied Commander during the battle who later became President of the United States",
          "answer": "Dwight David “Ike” Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorful commander of the U.S. Third Army who led the counterattack that relieved the 101st Airborne A",
          "answer": [
            "George S. Patton III",
            "George S. Patton Jr."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Heavily forested region of Belgium and Luxembourg where the battle took place",
          "answer": "Ardennes Forest"
        },
        {
          "question": "British commander who took charge of the northern half of the defense during this battle",
          "answer": "Bernard Law Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Besieged key road junction defended by the 101st Airborne Division during this battle R",
          "answer": "Bastogne"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Germans named the battle “Operation Watch on” this 2nd longest central European river",
          "answer": "Rhine"
        },
        {
          "question": "One-word response of Brigadier General Anthony McAuliffe to a surrender demand",
          "answer": "Nuts D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hundred Years War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "English king whose claim to the French throne caused it.",
          "answer": "Edward III"
        },
        {
          "question": "French heroine who was burned at the stake for witchcraft.",
          "answer": "Joan of Arc"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inheritance law that the French used to invalidate the English claim by disqualifying female inheritance.",
          "answer": "Salic Law"
        },
        {
          "question": "First battle won by English longbowmen, during which John of Bohemia was killed.",
          "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle won by Henry V on St. Crispin’s Day.",
          "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
        },
        {
          "question": "1340 naval battle in which the French navy was destroyed.",
          "answer": "Battle of Sluys"
        },
        {
          "question": "Peasant rebellion in northern France named for the term nobles used to refer to its participants.",
          "answer": "Jacquerie"
        },
        {
          "question": "French chronicler who described the history of the war from both sides.",
          "answer": "Jean Froissart IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Crimean War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire known as the Sick Man of Europe whose treatment of Christians was the immediate spark for F the war",
          "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nurse who became known as the Lady with the Lamp for her actions in the war",
          "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennyson poem about a failed attack at the Battle of Balaclava A",
          "answer": "The Charge of the Light Brigade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city and base of the Russian Black Sea Fleet whose fall led to the end of the war",
          "answer": "Sevastopol"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of War and Peace who served as a Russian artillery officer during the war",
          "answer": "Leo Tolstoy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular, descriptive name for the 93rd Highlanders that stopped the Russians at Balaclava R",
          "answer": "Thin Red Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island kingdom west of Italy that fought with the British and French forces",
          "answer": "Sardinia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian naval victory, the last major battle of sailed warships",
          "answer": "Sinope D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Last Ruler",
      "prompt": "Name the the last ruler...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Russia’s last tsar, later killed by the Bolsheviks",
          "answer": "Nicholas II"
        },
        {
          "question": "France’s last emperor who abdicated after the Franco-Prussian War",
          "answer": "Napoleon III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Germany’s last Kaiser, started and lost World War One",
          "answer": "Wilhelm II"
        },
        {
          "question": "No number needed – China’s last emperor, featured in the film The Last Emperor",
          "answer": [
            "Henry Pu-yi",
            "Xuantong Emperor,",
            "the Kangde Emperor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The last to call himself King of Ireland was this short-reigning British king",
          "answer": "Edward VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexico’s last emperor was this French puppet",
          "answer": "Maximilian I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greece’s last king, held this name which he shares with the victor at the Battle of the Milvian Bridge",
          "answer": "Constantine II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Brazil’s last emperor, overthrown in 1889 by a military dictatorship",
          "answer": "Pedro II Page 8 of 10"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Fifth Republic",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who led the Free French in World War Two before founding the Fifth Republic F",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defensive alliance from which France withdrew in 1966",
          "answer": [
            "NATO",
            "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which a period of civil unrest occurred in May, involving student riots and a strike",
          "answer": "1968 A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longest serving and first Socialist president of the Republic",
          "answer": "Francois Mitterrand"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who won re-election over Jean-Marie Le Pen in a landslide in 2002",
          "answer": "Jacques Chirac"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lower house of the bicameral French Parliament",
          "answer": [
            "National Assembly",
            "Assemblee nationale R"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Greenpeace ship bombed by French Intelligence in 1985",
          "answer": "Rainbow Warrior"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central African Republic dictator who the French overthrew in Operation Barracuda",
          "answer": "Jean-Bedel Bokassa D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This substance was the subject of the \"Letter to Queen Victoria\" sent by Commissioner Lin, who burned chests full of it on the beach. This substance was mixed with alcohol to make the eighteenth-century medicine (20 pts) ",
        "\"laudanum\" and was consumed in namesake \"dens.\" The seizure of the Arrow sparked a second (10 pts) ",
        "war named for this substance. For 10 points, identify this narcotic whose first war ended when the Treaty of Nanking granted European concessions in China."
      ],
      "answer": "opium"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Herbert Fairbank first explained the potential for this system in 1939 after expanding the Pershing Map. This system was authorized by a 1956 law but not completed until 1992, at a cost of 114 (20 pts) ",
        "billion dollars. This system was championed by Dwight Eisenhower, who had seen the uses of the (10 pts) ",
        "Autobahn system while serving in Germany. For 10 points, identify this road network which includes even-numbered east-west routes and odd-numbered north-south routes."
      ],
      "answer": "Interstate, Interstate Highway System, interstate highways"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roger Ascham described the use of this weapon in the manual Toxophilus, and it survived in the British army until World War II, when Jack Churchill killed a Nazi soldier with one of them. These weapons were sometimes named for the (20 pts) ",
        "Welsh people who invented them and perfected their use, and they were used to great effect by the English at (10 pts) ",
        "Agincourt (pr. AA-jin-core). For 10 points, name this six-foot-tall archery weapon which replaced the crossbow."
      ],
      "answer": "longbow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man won a Nobel Prize in Literature for his History of the English-Speaking Peoples. This man was First Lord of the Admiralty during the (20 pts) ",
        "Gallipoli disaster, though his \"wilderness years\" eventually ended and allowed him to make the \"we shall (10 pts) ",
        "fight them on the beaches\" speech. He was defeated in his first re-election bid by Clement Attlee. For 10 points, name this leader of the national unity government of the U.K. during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Winston Churchill, Churchill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this organization were represented in the Reichstag by the Centre Party. This organization was targeted by Adalbert von Falk's May Laws, part of the (20 pts) ",
        "Kulturkampf (pr. KOOL-tur-kompf) against it launched by Otto von Bismarck. A leader of this organization who was accused of turning a blind eye to the Holocaust was (10 pts) ",
        "Pius XII. For 10 points, name this organization which is the predominant Christian denomination in southern Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church, Catholic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A person by this name was the fanatically Catholic Duke of Guise (pr. GHEEZ) while\nanother man of this name was the final king of the Valois (pr. val-WAH) Dynasty. Another\nman of this name was originally the king of (20 pts) ",
        "Navarre and said \"Paris is worth a mass\" to\nexplain his conversion to Catholicism. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, give this name of three men who fought\nthe last French War of Religion, including the first Bourbon king of France."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Henry",
        "Henri"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) A major terrorist group in this country absorbed the Socialist Patients' Collective, a group\nwhich believes that people with illnesses were the oppressed class in capitalist societies, and\nlaunched a 1977 campaign known as its \"autumn.\" This home of the (20 pts) ",
        "Red Army Faction\nwas also where members of (10 pts) ",
        "Black September targeted athletes in 1972. For 10 points, name\nthis country where terrorist incidents included the attack on Israelis at the Munich Olympics."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "West Germany",
        "Germany"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) These people were sought out due to the new doctrine of \"limpieza de sangre\" (pr. leempee-EY-zuh day SAHN-gray), or \"cleanliness of blood.\" These people were given a\nderogatory nickname meaning (20 pts) ",
        "\"pig\" and were subject to the public \"auto de fe\" (pr.\nOW-toe deh FAY) if found. Tomas de Torquemada gave these people three months to leave (10 pts) ",
        "Spain in 1492. For 10 points, name these people whom the Inquisition sought to find\nsurvivals of within the \"conversos\" community."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish former Jews",
        "Jews",
        "secret Jews"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man successfully completed the \"red line\" map as part of the plan for a \"Cape to\nCairo railway.\" This man was sent as the agent of the Rothschild company to (20 pts) ",
        "Kimberley, where he spent seventeen years buying competing diamond fields. He founded\nthe (10 pts) ",
        "De Beers company to cement his monopoly over the industry. For 10 points, name this\nBritish colonialist in South Africa who endowed a series of scholarships for foreign students at\nOxford."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cecil Rhodes",
        "Rhodes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hochwald was one of this entity’s over one hundred ouvrages. This entity also included\ndesignated flood zones, but it was not extended to the (20 pts) ",
        "English Channel. It was named\nafter the minister of War who proposed it, and it failed to protect the (10 pts) ",
        "Ardennes forest.\nFor ten points, name this defensive line built by the French to protect against German invasion, which\nfailed when the Nazis avoided it by invading through Belgium instead."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Maginot Line",
        "Maginot"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1855, Napoleon III commissioned a classification system for this commodity, produced\nby Haut-Brion and Chateau Margaux. Prominent (20 pts) ",
        "growing regions for this product\ninclude France’s “golden slope,” though the 1976 Judgment of Paris proved the quality of (10 pts) ",
        "California’s production of varieties like Cabernet Sauvignon. For ten points, name this alcoholic\nbeverage produced in Burgundy and Bordeaux from grapes."
      ],
      "answer": "wine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Foreigners such as the Scotsman Thomas Gordon were often invited to lead this\norganization. One portion of this organization nearly sparked (20 pts) ",
        "war with Great Britain\nwhile being deployed to relieve another part of this organization, which had been bottled up\nin Port Arthur. That force would proceed to have its T crossed by (10 pts) ",
        "Heihachiro Togo and\nbe destroyed at the Battle of Tsushima Straits. The Baltic and Pacific fleets were part of, for ten points,\nwhat military organization, which experienced a revolt on the battleship Potemkin?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Imperial Russian Navy",
        "Russian Navy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Percy and Charles Neville attempted to overthrow this monarch in the Rising\nof the North. This monarch supported the Dutch in one conflict by signing the Treaty of\nNonsuch, and Francis Walsingham uncovered a plot to assassinate this monarch by Anthony (20 pts) ",
        "Babington, which led to the execution of this monarch’s cousin, Mary Stuart. This\nmonarch spoke of having a “heart and stomach of a (10 pts) ",
        "king” in a speech to troops at Tilbury.\nThe Spanish Armada targeted, for ten points, what “Virgin Queen” of England?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Elizabeth I of England",
        "Elizabeth I",
        "Queen Elizabeth I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man involved in this event used the name John Johnson, and people involved in\nthis event took shelter at the Holbeche House. Francis (20 pts) ",
        "Tresham and Thomas Wintour\nwere executed for their role in this event, and the plan for this event was uncovered in an\nanonymous letter sent to Lord (10 pts) ",
        "Monteagle. Robert Catesby served as the leader behind this\nevent, which saw Guy Fawkes discovered guarding ammunition. For ten points, name this plot to blow up\nthe British Parliament and assassinate James I."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gunpowder Plot",
        "Gunpowder",
        "Treason"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group sometimes dressed in women’s clothing as their founder’s “wives,” and\ncarried out their acts using a tool they called “Great Enoch.” This group first appeared in\nNottingham and were threatened with (20 pts) ",
        "capital punishment with the Frame Breaking\nAct. E. J. Hobsbawm referred to their (10 pts) ",
        "sabotage as “collective bargaining by riot.” For ten\npoints, what British textile workers in the early 19th century smashed machines that were replacing their\nlabor and now give their name to those who oppose technological progress?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Luddites"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Duc de Longueville represented the French during the negotiations of this treaty.\nDespite this treaty, Spain and France did not cease hostilities until the Treaty of the (20 pts) ",
        "Pyrenees, and Sweden annexed Bremen after the signature of this treaty. It affirmed the\nindependence of Switzerland and the Netherlands, and it extended the (10 pts) ",
        "Peace of Augsburg\nby allowing Calvinism to be a German state’s official religion. For ten points, name this peace treaty that\nended the Thirty Years War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Peace of Westphalia",
        "Treaty of Westphalia",
        "Westphalia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The fall of this government led to the deportation of many to New Caledonia. Gustave\nCourbet was a member of this government, which ordered the fall of the (20 pts) ",
        "Vendome\nColumn. Many of this government’s officials were executed on the Wall of the Federalists in\nPere Lachaise Cemetery. (10 pts) ",
        "Marshall MacMahon led an army that repressed this government during\nthe “Bloody Week”. For ten points, name this radical socialist government that formed in the French\ncapital in 1871."
      ],
      "answer": "Paris Commune"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Aaron rationed battery power during this event. Ken Mattingly was supposed to\nhave participated in this event but was unable due to (20 pts) ",
        "German Measles, while Fred\nHaise suffered a serious urinary tract infection during it. During this event, the service (10 pts) ",
        "module’s number 2 oxygen tank suffered a failure, causing Jack Swigert and Jim Lovell to report\n“Houston, we’ve had a problem”. For ten points, name this NASA mission whose moon landing was\naborted but which returned safely to Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "Apollo 13"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Dog Tax War was begun by members of this ethnic group. Europeans allying with\nthese people were known as “Pakeha.” Te Kooti founded a form of Christianity that likened\nthe (20 pts) ",
        "plight of these people to that of the Israelites; that religion is Ringatu. This group\nsuffered great losses as a result of the (10 pts) ",
        "Musket Wars. For ten points, name these people believed\nto have arrived in New Zealand from Polynesia in the 13th century."
      ],
      "answer": "Maori"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle’s highest ranking English casualty was Edward, Duke of York. The Siege of\nHarfleur preceded this battle, whose losers raided an enemy (20 pts) ",
        "baggage train, causing\nthe winning commander to order prisoner executions. One side in this battle drove sharp\nwooden stakes in front of their position; heavy rain then trapped (10 pts) ",
        "Charles d’Albret’s cavalry\nin deep mud at the mercy of massed English longbows. For ten points, name this 1415 battle of the\nHundred Years War, a victory for Henry V."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Agincourt",
        "Agincourt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Operation Harvest Festival was this event’s largest single action. The Einsatzgruppen\nwere used to carry out this event. At the Wannsee Conference [VAHN-zay Conference],\nit was proposed that (20 pts) ",
        "Scandinavia would not be subject to this event, and ferries to\nSweden thus protected many Danes from it. The Nuremberg (10 pts) ",
        "Trials prosecuted many\nplanners of this event, which was described as the Final Solution. Dachau and Auschwitz were sites of\nconcentration camps during, for ten points, what genocide of Jews and other “undesirables” by Nazi\nGermany during World War II?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Holocaust",
        "Shoah"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This kingdom bought the province of Neumark from the Teutonic Order and attempted\nto establish hegemony with the creation of a customs union called the Zollverein. It\nwas formed after a union of its namesake duchy, now known as (20 pts) ",
        "Kaliningrad, with\nBrandenburg under the Hohenzollern dynasty. This country’s army was reformed by (10 pts) ",
        "Frederick Wilhelm I, making it the most disciplined force in Europe. For ten points, name this kingdom,\nthe largest of the states that founded Germany, with capital at Berlin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Prussia",
        "Prussia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A monarch of this name commanded troops at the Battle of Dettingen, the last time\na British king did so. Another king of this name was the last British king born outside of\nBritain. Robert (20 pts) ",
        "Walpole, the first prime minister of Great Britain, served under a\nmonarch of this name. A ruler with this name came to power after the abdication of (10 pts) ",
        "Edward VIII and was the father of Queen Elizabeth. For ten points, give this name of six British kings,\nthe third of which opposed American independence."
      ],
      "answer": "George"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler chartered the Levant Company in an attempt to form a trade alliance with\nthe Ottoman Empire. This ruler supported the Netherlands through the Treaty of Nonsuch\nand attacked their enemy at Cadiz with the help of privateer (20 pts) ",
        "Francis Drake. During the\nTilbury speech, this ruler declared that she had the “body of a weak and feeble woman” but\nthe “heart and stomach” of a king while rallying her men against the (10 pts) ",
        "Spanish Armada. For\nten points, name this daughter of Anne Boleyn who succeeded her sister Mary I to become the “Virgin\nQueen” of England."
      ],
      "answer": "Elizabeth I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man suppressed an insurrection by ordering a “whiff of grapeshot” on the 13th\nVendemaire. This man first achieved fame commanding the artillery at the Siege of (20 pts) ",
        "Toulon. This man attempted to reach British possessions in India by invading Egypt, and\nhe returned from exile on the island of (10 pts) ",
        "Elba in his Hundred Days, at the end of which he was\ndefeated by Gebhard von Bl¨ucher and the Duke of Wellington. For ten points, name this French emperor,\nwho was defeated at the Battle of Waterloo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Napoleon I",
        "Napoleon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. These two countries first operated together in the disastrous\nsiege of Newport, during which the forces of John Sullivan were abandoned and slaughtered.\nA diplomat from one of these two countries attempted to recruit (20 pts) ",
        "privateers in the\nother country to fight Spain, almost leading to his deportation. During a diplomatic meeting\nbetween these two countries, the response, “no, no, not a (10 pts) ",
        "sixpence!” was given to a request\nfor a bribe to see Charles Talleyrand. The XYZ affair occurred between, for ten points, what two countries\nthat agreed to the Louisiana Purchase?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "France and the United States of America",
        "France and US",
        "France and United States"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country antagonized a neighbor via the Hallstein Doctrine, a brief policy of breaking\ndiplomatic relations with countries that officially recognized that neighbor. Foreign agents\nwithin this country sponsored the far-left (20 pts) ",
        "Red Army Faction, which was co-founded by\nAndreas Baader. This country tried to improve relations with its neighbor via ostpolitik, as\nsupported by (10 pts) ",
        "Willy Brandt. This country was divided into British, American, and French zones via\nan agreement at the Yalta conference. For ten points, name this European country that, in 1990, re-united\nwith its eastern neighbor."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "West Germany",
        "Federal Republic of Germany",
        "FRG"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man’s attempt to avoid conflict was documented in a telegram to “cousin\nWilly.” Father Gapon’s insurrection took place during the reign of this ruler, who was\npersuaded to sign the (20 pts) ",
        "October manifesto after angering the populace on Bloody\nSunday. In the mid-20th century, numerous imposters claimed to be this man’s (10 pts) ",
        "daughter, Anastasia, who was killed with the rest of this man’s family by the Bolsheviks in 1918.\nFor ten points, name this final Romanov Tsar of Russia."
      ],
      "answer": "Nicholas II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This government’s attempt to unify Protestantism was opposed by Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s\nConfessing Church. The Red Orchestra and White Rose groups opposed this government,\nwhich attacked modernist art at the (20 pts) ",
        "Degenerate Art Exhibition. Leni Riefenstahl’s film\nTriumph of the Will was produced with the help of Joseph (10 pts) ",
        "Goebbels, this government’s\npropaganda minister. For ten points, name this regime that created the Nuremberg Laws to persecute\nJews before engineering the Holocaust."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nazi Germany",
        "Nazi",
        "Germany",
        "National Socialist German Workers’ Party",
        "NSGWP",
        "the Third Reich"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This nation, which conquered the German base of Tsingtao during World War\nI as part of its alliance with Britain, joined Britain, Italy, and France as permanent\nmembers on the League of Nations’ executive council. The (20 pts) ",
        "Doolittle raids\nattacked this country. Economic conglomerates called (10 pts) ",
        "zaibatsu were created in, for ten\npoints, what Asian empire that annexed neighboring Korea in 1910 and was led by Hideki Tojo in\nWorld War II?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Empire of Japan",
        "Japan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Many years after this battle, Henry Dearborn sparked a public controversy by publishing a critique of his commanding officer’s actions during it. A John Trumbull painting depicts Joseph Warren’s (20 pts)",
        "death during this battle. Forces led by William Prescott and Israel Putnam rebuffed a British attack at this battle. The order “Don’t (10 pts)",
        "fire until you see the whites of their eyes” was probably given at, for ten points, what 1775 battle, mostly fought on Breed’s Hill outside Boston?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Bunker Hill",
        "Battle of Breed’s Hill before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man employed logs to hamper paratroop landings, a tactic that became known as his namesake Asparagus when this man oversaw defenses at the Atlantic (20 pts)",
        "Wall. While this man recovered from injuries sustained in a strafing raid, he was offered cyanide pills after he was implicated in the Valkyrie assassination plot against (10 pts)",
        "Hitler. This general fought an indecisive battle against Bernard Montgomery at El Alamein. For ten points, name this “Desert Fox” who commanded Germany’s Afrika Korps."
      ],
      "answer": "Erwin Rommel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On a voyage to Panama, this man made a detour to attack the Canary Islands at the Battle of Las Palmas. During his Great Expedition, this privateer raided St. Augustine. With his cousin John Hawkins, this man organized (20 pts)",
        "fireships and won against a fleet led by the Duke of Medina Sidonia. In 1587, this captain raided Cadiz, “singing the beard of the King of Spain,” seven years after a landmark voyage on the (10 pts)",
        "Golden Hind. For ten points, name this man, the first Englishman to circumnavigate the globe, who was employed by Elizabeth I and fought the Spanish Armada."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir Francis Drake"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the Mexican Expedition, six members of this group bayonet charged 3,000 Mexican soldiers at the Battle of Camaron. The “spilled blood” provision automatically grants members of this group (20 pts)",
        "citizenship after they are wounded in combat. This organization was formed after the July Revolution overthrew the House of Bourbon. During World War II, this section of the military refused to cooperate with the (10 pts)",
        "Vichy government. For ten points, name this branch of the French military primarily consisting of non-French volunteers."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "French Foreign Legion",
        "FFL",
        "L´egion E´trang`ere",
        "LE"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was advised by the half-French Poker Joe, and despite being previously absent, he led forces to victory at the Battle of White Bird Canyon. After having led his forces hundreds of miles from his native Wallowa Valley, this leader was finally defeated by (20 pts)",
        "Oliver Howard at the Battle of Bear Paw. After this man’s 1877 surrender to Nelson Miles, he declared “From where the (10 pts)",
        "sun now stands, I will fight no more forever.” For ten points, name this Nez Perce chief who fiercely resisted attempts at relocation."
      ],
      "answer": "Chief Joseph"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. Tim Clayton argued that this legend was promoted by James Gillray cartoons like “Little Boney in a Strong Fit” and one in which the central figure carves up the world with a British prime minister. This legend supposedly stems from a 5-unit difference between British and (20 pts)",
        "French systems of measurement. This myth allegedly explains why its central figure disapproved of Josephine’s (10 pts)",
        "high heels, and it is supported by a misunderstanding of the nickname le petit caporal [“le petite corporal”]. Jokes have often been made about, for ten points, what misconception about the physical stature of a French emperor?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Napoleon Bonaparte was very short",
        "equivalent descriptions",
        "descriptions of the actual truth, like Napoleon wasn’t that short"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This location was the site of a 1947 defense treaty expanded on by the Treaty of Brussels the following year. At this location, the Conde Louis was defeated by Turenne in the Battle of the Dunes during the Franco-Spanish War. Gerd von Rundstedt gave a (20 pts)",
        "halt order during an assault on this location, allowing one side to launch Operation Dynamo with the help of numerous civilian ships. A (10 pts)",
        "2017 Christopher Nolan film depicts fighting at, for ten points, what location near the Belgian/French border from which the British Expeditionary Force was evacuated in 1940?"
      ],
      "answer": "Dunkirk"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man forced the surrender of William Hull by repeatedly marching his troops through the woods to create the impression of bigger numbers. This man allegedly proclaimed “now here is a man!” after meeting Isaac Brock. This man’s forces swelled after the (20 pts)",
        "New Madrid [MA-drid] earthquake was interpreted as an omen. Two years after this man’s brother, (10 pts)",
        "known as “the Prophet,” was defeated at Tippecanoe, this man was killed at the Battle of the Thames. For ten points, name this Shawnee chief who led a namesake confederacy in support of the British during the War of 1812."
      ],
      "answer": "Tecumseh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man allegedly commented “they shoot like pigs” after surviving a machine gun ambush that served as the basis for Frederick Forsyth’s The Day of the Jackal. This man’s car drove away despite two punctured (20 pts)",
        "tires in that assassination attempt. The OAS, which opposed this man’s signing of the (10 pts)",
        "Evian Accords, plotted that 1962 assassination attempt, for which Jean Bastien-Thiry was killed by the last firing squad in France. For ten points, name this founder of the Fifth Republic and leader of Free France."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One member of this group attained her nickname for the sound she made when pinched by George Spahn; that member, “Squeaky” Fromme, conducted a failed assassination attempt on Gerald Ford. (20 pts)",
        "Roman Polanski was filming in Europe when his wife was killed by members of this group, whose leader believed in the coming of a race war called (10 pts)",
        "“Helter Skelter.” This group was formed after its leader moved to San Francisco during the Summer of Love. For ten points, name this criminal “family” whose members killed Sharon Tate and several other people."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Manson family",
        "the Mansons"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This region was the target of Operation Chastise, where the so-called “Dambuster” bouncing torpedo bombs struck the Mohne and Edersee dams to cause massive flooding. A namesake International Authority attempting to wrest control of this region was abandoned after (20 pts)",
        "Konrad Adenauer agreed to put its resources under the European Coal and Steel Community. Along with the (10 pts)",
        "Saarland, French troops were deployed in this region until reparations could be repaid at the end of World War I. Gelsenkirchen and Dortmund are cities of, for ten points, what steel producing valley of Germany?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ruhr Valley"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this dynasty came to power after defeated his brother Sviatopolk and passed a law code called the Russkaya Pravda. Another ruler of this dynasty converted to (20 pts)",
        "Christianity when he learned about the Islamic prohibition on alcohol and led a 988 mass baptism of his kingdom. The founding of this dynasty was described in the Primary Chronicle. This dynasty ended after (10 pts)",
        "Feodor I was succeeded by Michael Romanov in 1613. For ten points name this dynasty that ruled the Kievan Rus, and later Russia, until the Time of Troubles."
      ],
      "answer": "Rurikid Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler with this name adopted the surname “Mikhailov” before meeting with William III and traveling through Western Europe, but his tall stature made it hard to go completely unnoticed during his “Grand (20 pts)",
        "Embassy.” The first ruler with this name imposed a tax on the (10 pts)",
        "beards of the Boyars as part of his efforts to modernize Russia. For ten points, name this “great” Russian tsar who established a large port city on the Baltic Sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Peter the Great or Peter I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Operation RYAN was conducted by this agency. Robert Hanssen received 15 life sentences for collaborating with this agency, whose predecessors included the NKVD. A group of British recruits who became known as the (20 pts)",
        "Cambridge Five worked with this organization. A member of this organization named Rudolf Abel was (10 pts)",
        "exchanged for downed U2 pilot Gary Powers. Vladimir Putin once served as an officer in, for ten points, what Soviet intelligence agency?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "KGB or Komitet gosudarstvennoy bezopasnosti",
        "or the Committee for State Security"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alexandre Gonsse de Rougeville attempted to save this monarch in the Carnation Plot. This royal’s signature was forged in an attempt to sell expensive jewelry in the (20 pts)",
        "Affair of the Diamond Necklace. The Petit Trianon, originally designed for Madame de Pompadour, was given to this woman. This woman was forced to flee to (10 pts)",
        "Tuileries Palace under the watch of the Marquis de Lafayette after a crowd seized Versailles. For ten points, name this wife of Louis XVI who legendarily said “Let them eat cake” during the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader fabricated the “Doctors” Plot” in order to arrest political enemies. The Holodomor was likely organized by this leader to reduce the population of the (20 pts)",
        "Ukraine. The New Economic Policy was rejected by this leader, who instead implemented five-year plans. This man ordered the (10 pts)",
        "NKVD to carry out the “Great Purge,” which left the Red Army unprepared to deal with an eventual German invasion. For ten points, name this “man of steel” who led the Soviet Union through World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Stalin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this family sent the adviser Drouyn to resolve the Luxembourg dispute with (20 pts)",
        "Prussia. In 1864, a member of this family overthrew the government of Benito Juarez to place the Hapsburg (10 pts)",
        "Maximillian I on the throne of Mexico. Another member of this family seized control of Spain, sparking the Peninsular War. For ten points, name this family that had two Emperors of France, both named Napoleon."
      ],
      "answer": "Bonaparte"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was replaced by Leo von Caprivi after his ministers were allowed to report to the king. The Kartell, a right-wing parliamentary coalition, led by this man was opposed by the (20 pts)",
        "Centre Party and the Social Democrats. This man supported Adalbert Falk’s May Laws, which targeted the (10 pts)",
        "Catholic Church as part of his “kulturkampf.” In one speech, this man said that the questions of the day would be answered with “iron and blood.” For ten points, name this Chancellor of Prussia who created Germany."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Otto von Bismarck",
        "Otto Eduard Leopold"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Three bright arcs around this object were named for the motto of the French Revolution. George Airy was blamed for the British team failure to discover this object first after Johann Galle used calculations by Urbain Le (20 pts)",
        "Verrier to do so. This planet, whose largest moon is Triton, was the final one visited by Voyager 2, which observed a Great (10 pts)",
        "Dark Spot on it. For ten points, name this planet that, after the demotion of Pluto, regained its status as the farthest planet from the Sun."
      ],
      "answer": "Neptune"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This monarch negotiated the return of Calais by signing the Treaty of Vervins with Philip II. The Battle of Ivry, a decisive battle with the (20 pts)",
        "Catholic League, was won by this monarch. This man, after defeating the Duke of Guise, legendarily converted to Catholicism by saying that (10 pts)",
        "“Paris is well worth a mass.” The Bourbon Dynasty was founded by this man who ended the French Wars of Religion. For ten points, name this French King who granted Huguenots religious freedom in the Edict of Nantes."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Henry IV of France",
        "Good King Henry",
        "Henry the Great",
        "Henry III of Navarre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Soldiers on the losing side at this battle were given until the 25th of August to surrender in exchange for a full pardon. The Duke of Schomberg was among the leaders of the winning side killed at this battle, which was followed by the Declaration of (20 pts)",
        "Finglas. One side fled to Limerick following this battle, where they successfully fended off a siege. (10 pts)",
        "Dutch Blue Guards were employed by the winning side of this battle fought near a namesake river. For ten points, name this 1690 victory for William of Orange, after which James II fled the British Isles."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of the Boyne"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man boasted that defeating the British would be as easy as eating breakfast. This Dman refused to reinforce La Haye Sainte, and his cannons were nullified by the reverse slope defense. A fatal charge by (20 pts)",
        "Marshal Ney against retreating Englishmen was ordered by this man. This man deployed his troops from Plancenoit in order to capture Hougoumont but was hampered by the late arrival of Gebhard von Blucher at this man’s (10 pts)",
        "final defeat. For ten points, name this Frenchman who died 1200 miles off the west coast of Africa on the island of Saint Helena."
      ],
      "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A monument displaying a boot belonging to this man honors his best known victory, though he was less successful leading a siege of Quebec during which his leg was severely A injured for the first time. This man was forced to flee aboard the ship (20 pts)",
        "Vulture after meeting with Major John Andre, an action prompted by this man’s anger that he had not received credit for helping (10 pts)",
        "win the Battle of Saratoga. For ten points, name this general who planned to transfer Fort Ticonderoga to the British, whose name is now a synonym for “traitor.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these two countries refused to use force to put down the revolt of Colonel Ahmed Urabi, prompting the other to intervene militarily. Another incident between these two countries featured a territorial dispute in Sudan and ended with a troop standoff in (20 pts)",
        "Fashoda. These two countries later worked with David Ben-Gurion in Operation Musketeer, deploying paratroopers to thwart Gamel Abdel Nasser’s (10 pts)",
        "nationalization of a waterway. For ten points, name these two European powers that joined forces in the Suez Crisis."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United Kingdom",
        "UK, Britain,",
        "England and France 3RNicolay de Caveri created one of these items based on another that a fellow countryman smuggled out of Portugal. Fifty-three of these were collected by Abraham Ortelius to create the Theatrum Orbis Terrarum. The preservation of + angles in a 1569 object of this type resulted in several key distortions. Martin Waldeseemuller’s Universalis Cosmographia was an object of this type in which the name * Amerigo Vespucci was used to identify certain new landmasses. The Mercator Projection is an example of, for ten points, what cartographic objects? ANSWER: Maps D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Max Eastman translated a three-volume history written by this man as well as a work in which this man claims that one leader is engaging in ineffective “zigzags” in economic policy. That work by this man accuses a rival of engaging in “Bonapartism” and is titled (20 pts)",
        "The Revolution Betrayed. In one essay, this man claims that “the task of arming the F revolution falls with all its weight upon the proletariat,” which is in reference to his desire to maintain the (10 pts)",
        "Red Army that he created. For ten points, name this Leftist Russian revolutionary whose assassination was ordered by Stalin."
      ],
      "answer": "Leon Trotsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler ignited one rebellion after appointing Yuri Dolgoruki to round up fugitive peasants in lands that were led by Kondraty Bulavin. This ruler signed the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Constantinople with Mustafa II, which led to this ruler creating his country’s first naval base at Taganrog. This ruler instituted a Beard Tax for (10 pts)",
        "Boyars after he traveled incognito F to observe a Dutch shipyard as part of his Grand Embassy. For ten points, name this Tsar whose reforms modernized 18th century Russia."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Peter I",
        "Peter the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Desmond Young wrote the popular first biography of this man, which propagated his namesake “myth” of being an apolitical figure. This man referred to a defensive framework extending to the Qattara Depression as the “Devil’s gardens.” This man won the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Kasserine Pass while fighting in Tunisia. For his alleged role in Operation Valkyrie, F this man was asked to commit suicide by Adolf Hitler. Nicknamed the (10 pts)",
        "“Desert Fox,” For ten points, name this commander of the Afrika Corps, a German general during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Erwin Rommel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The original sets for this work were designed by Nicholas Roerich, and grace notes in the opening lines of this work are used to imitate human voices. This work was the third by its composer that he created for Russian impresario Sergei Diaghilev, the founder of the A (20 pts)",
        "Paris-based Ballets Russes. Choreographed by Vaslav Nijinsky, this work ends with a young girl dancing herself to death in a sacrifical ritual, and the Paris (10 pts)",
        "premiere of this work caused a riot. For ten points, name this 1913 ballet depicting “Pagan Russia,” composed by Igor Stravinsky."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Rite of Spring",
        "Le Sacre du printemps"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Battle of Klushino during this period resulted in a group of seven nobles offering their support for Prince Wladyslaw. Marina Mneszich was appointed queen during this A period thanks to an invasion led by (20 pts)",
        "Sigismund III of Poland. Three men known as the False Dmitris attempted to claim the throne during this period that began after the death of Feodor led to the end of the (10 pts)",
        "Rurik dynasty. For ten points, identify this period of turmoil in Russian history that ended with the coronation of Michael Romanov."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Time of Troubles",
        "Smuta"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "These specific people were banned from working on the Sabbath in the \"Manifesto of three-day Corvee [[kor-VEH]]\" passed by Paul I. During the \"Forbidden Years,\" the hardship of the (*) Livonian wars and crop failure led to these specific people losing their right to move from their estate. These people paid a rent known as obrok to the landed (*) boyars they served. In 1861, Alexander II emancipated, for ten points, what peasant class of Russia?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Russian Serfs",
        "Krepostnoy Krest'yanin",
        "Peasants before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Shapley-Curtis debate centered on whether or not this structure was a \"spiral nebula.\" The center of this structure contains a radio source discovered in 1931 by Karl Jansky, the supermassive black hole Sagittarius (20 pts)",
        "A-star, and this structure was believed by the Babylonians to be the severed tail of a dragoness. Orbited by Large and Small Clouds named for (10 pts)",
        "Ferdinand Magellan, for ten points, what is this galaxy which is home to the Sun and Earth? ANSWER:Milky Waygalaxy (3) Thiscitywasfoundedin1565byPedroMenéndezdeAvilés[[ah-vee-LEHS]]on the feast day of the patron of brewers.HenryFlaglerbuiltarailroadthroughthiscity, which was annexed into the U.S. along with the rest of its stateintheAdams-Onís(+) Treaty. This city was intended to be turned into a winter resort by an industrialist who constructed the Hotel Alcazar and Hotel Ponce de Leon. (*) For ten points, name this Florida city, the oldest continuously-inhabited European settlement in the United States. ANSWER:St. Augustine(orSan Agustín) (4) With his lover, this crown prince planned to flee to England and potentially usurpthethronefromhisfatherduringtheKatte[[KAH-tuh]]Affair.Thefailureofthe Austrians and Russians to follow-up on the Battleof(+)Kunesdorfwasknownasthis king's \"Miracle of the House of Brandenburg.\" This German's victory in the Seven Years' War led tohiscountry'sannexationof(*)Silesia.Fortenpoints,namethis\"Great\" king of Prussia during the mid-18th century. ANSWER:Frederickthe Great (orFriedrichder Große[[\"GROSS\"-uh]]; acceptFrederick II; orFriedrichII; acceptOld Fritz; or DerAlteFritz) 2021-22 C Set History (5) The Bandeirantes [[bahn-deh-RAHN-tehs]] were adventurers in this modern nation who dressed like Jesuitstodupenativesintoenslavement.Thoseraidersoften spoke Língua Geral [[LEEN-gwah heh-RAHL], a (+) pidgin which mixed this country's European language with Tupi. This South American nation allied with Argentina and Uruguay in a \"Triple Alliance\" to halt Paraguayan aggression. Pedro (*) Cabral discovered, for the point, what large former Portuguese colony?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Federative Republic ofBrazilor RepúblicaFederativa doBrasil",
        "Kingdom ofBrazil",
        "or Reino doBrasil"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The loser of this battle sent his Imperial Guard to capture La Haye Sainte and Plancenoit [[PLAHN-sen-NWAH]] but was later pushed back by Foot Guards under Sir Peregrine (20 pts)",
        "Maitland. After his Prussians were defeated at the Battle of Ligny [[leen-YEE]], two days before this battle, Gebhard von Blücher [[BLOO-kuh]] withdrew north to (10 pts)",
        "Wavre [[WAHV]]. For ten points, name this 1815 battle at which the Seventh Coalition led by the Duke of Wellington ensured the final defeat of Napoleon Bonaparte."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Waterloo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In this year, England returned all continental possessions to the French, save Calais [[kah-LAY]], in the Peace of Étaples [[eh-TAHPL]]. The Jewish people of Spain were expelled or forced to convert in the Alhambra Decree (*) of this year, passed by Ferdinand and Isabella. In this year, the settlement of \"La Navidad\" was founded after the ship Santa Maria ran aground on Hispaniola. Christopher Columbus unintentionally (*) \"discovered\" the New World in, for ten points, what 15th century year?"
      ],
      "answer": "1492"
    }
  ]
}